<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-09-25T15:18:01+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JBall’s Site</title><subtitle>Jon Ball&apos;s personal site. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Milan kundera’s essay “the novel and europe”</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Milan-Kundera's-Essay-The-Novel-and-Europe/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Milan kundera’s essay “the novel and europe”"/><published>2025-09-25T00:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-09-25T00:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Milan%20Kundera&apos;s%20Essay%20%22The%20Novel%20and%20Europe%22</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Milan-Kundera&apos;s-Essay-The-Novel-and-Europe/"><![CDATA[<h1 id="the-novel-and-europe">The Novel and Europe</h1> <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan_Kundera"><strong>Milan Kundera</strong></a>, translated from the French by <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/David_Bellos"><strong>David Bellos</strong></a></p> <p>July 19, 1984 issue, The New York Review</p> <h3 id="1">1.</h3> <p>In 1935, three years before his death, Edmund Husserl gave his celebrated lectures in Vienna and Prague on the crisis of European humanity. For Husserl, “European” was not so much a term of geography (it could include America, for example) as a spiritual identity deriving from the philosophy of classical Greece. It was there that man first conceived of the world (the world as a whole) as a question to answer. The Greeks questioned the world not in order to satisfy this or that practical need, but because “the passion of knowing had seized mankind.”</p> <p>The crisis Husserl spoke of seemed to him so profound that he wondered whether Europe was in a position to survive it. The roots of the crisis lay for him at the beginning of the Modern Era, in Galileo and Descartes, in the onesidedness of European science, which, in reducing the world to an object of technical and mathematical investigation, had put <em>die Lebenswelt</em>, the world of concrete living, beyond its pale.</p> <p>The rise of science propelled man into the tunnels of specialized knowledge. With every step forward in scientific knowledge, the less clearly he could see either the world as a whole or his own self, and he plunged further into what Husserl’s pupil Heidegger called in a beautiful and almost magical phrase “the forgetting of being.”</p> <p>Brought up by Descartes to be the “master and possessor of nature,” man becomes a mere thing before those forces (technology, politics, history) which pass his understanding, exceed his grasp, and grasp him. For those forces, man’s concrete being, his “living world” (<em>Lebenswelt</em>) has no value and no interest: it is eclipsed and forgotten.</p> <h3 id="2">2.</h3> <p>This critical view of the Modern Era is reminiscent of Solzhenitsyn’s notion that the European crisis began with the Renaissance, and that all subsequent history is but a process of decay.</p> <p>But I don’t think the two great phenomenologists rejected the Modern Era. It would be fairer to say that they unveiled the ambiguity of this epoch which—like all that is human—contains in its birth the seed of its demise. Such ambiguity in no way diminishes the last four centuries of European culture, to which I feel all the more attached since I am not a philosopher but a novelist. And for me, the founder of the Modern Era is not just Descartes, but also Cervantes.</p> <p>If one accepts as a hypothesis that philosophy and science have ignored man’s being, then it is even clearer that Cervantes gave birth to a great European art which is nothing other than the perpetual investigation of the being ignored by science.</p> <p>You have only to open <em>Being and Time</em> to realize that all the existential themes analyzed by Heidegger had already been uncovered, demonstrated, studied by four centuries of novel-writing. The novel discovered the different dimensions of existence one by one: with Cervantes and his contemporaries, it questioned the nature of adventure; with Richardson, it began to examine “what happens inside” and to unmask the secret life of feelings; with Balzac, it discovered man’s rootedness in history; with Flaubert, it explored the <em>terra</em> previously <em>incognita</em> of the everyday; with Tolstoy, it focused on the role of the irrational in human behavior and decisions. It measured time: the evanescent past with Proust, the evanescent present with Joyce. With Thomas Mann, it queried the role of the myths that control our movements from the remote past of man. And so on, and so on.</p> <p>The novel has accompanied man uninterruptedly and faithfully since the beginning of the Modern Era. It was then that the “passion of knowing,” which Husserl considered to be the essence of European spirituality, seized the novel and led it to observe man’s concrete life closely, and to protect him from “the forgetting of being.” That is the sense in which I understand and share Hermann Broch’s obstinately repeated point that the only <em>raison d’être</em> of a novel is to discover what can only be discovered by a novel. A novel that does not uncover a hitherto unknown segment of existence is immoral. Knowledge is the novel’s only morality.</p> <p>I would also add: the novel is Europe’s creation; its discoveries, though made in different languages, belong to the whole continent. The <em>sequence of discoveries</em> (not the sum of what was written) is what constitutes the history of the European novel. It is only in its context that the value of a work (that is to say, the import of its discovery) can be fully seen and understood.</p> <h3 id="3">3.</h3> <p>As God slowly departed from the seat whence he had controlled the universe and its order of values, told good from evil, and given a sense to each thing, then Don Quixote came out of his mansion and was no longer able to recognize the world. In the absence of the supreme arbiter, the world suddenly acquired a fearsome ambiguity. The single divine truth decomposed into myriad relative truths shared among men. Thus was born the world of the Modern Era, and with it the novel—the image and model of that world—sprang to life.</p> <p>To take Descartes’s “thinking self” as the basis of everything and to be alone before the universe is to adopt an attitude which Hegel was right to call heroic.</p> <p>To take the world as relative, as Cervantes did, to be obliged to face not a single absolute truth but a heap of contradictory truths (truths embodied in <em>imaginary thinking selves</em> called characters), to have as one’s only certainty the <em>wisdom of uncertainty</em>, requires no less courage.</p> <p>Who’s right and who’s wrong? Don Quixote, or the others? Much has been written on the question. Some see in Cervantes’s novel a rationalist critique of Don Quixote’s woolly idealism. Others see the novel as a celebration of the same idealism. Both interpretations are mistaken because they both try to find at the novel’s source not a question but a moral judgment.</p> <p>Man desires a world where good and evil are clearly distinguished. He has an innate and inextinguishable tendency to make judgments before he understands. Religions and ideologies are founded on this desire. But they can cope with the novel only by translating its language of relativity and ambiguity into their own apodictic and dogmatic tongue. They require someone to be right: either Anna Karenina is the victim of a blinkered tyrant, or Karenin is the victim of an immoral woman; either K., crushed by an unjust court, is innocent, or the court stands for divine justice and K. is guilty.</p> <p>This “either–or” encapsulates an inability to bear the essential relativity of human affairs, an inability to come face to face with the absence of a supreme arbiter. This inability means that the novel’s wisdom (the wisdom of uncertainty) is hard to accept or to grasp.</p> <h3 id="4">4.</h3> <p>Don Quixote set off on his adventures into a wide-open world: he could go out and come home as he pleased. All novels of this first period are journeys into an apparently unbounded universe. The opening of Diderot’s <em>Jacques le fataliste</em>, for example, finds Jacques and his master in the middle of a journey; we don’t know where they’ve come from or where they’re going. The two characters exist in a time without beginning or end, in a space devoid of boundaries, in the middle of a Europe that will go on forever.</p> <p>Half a century later, in Balzac, the distant horizons of Diderot disappear like a landscape disappearing behind the modern buildings of social institutions—the police, the law, the world of money and crime the army and the State. Time, in Balzac’s world, no longer idles happily by as it does for Cervantes and Diderot: it is propelled along the rails of History. It’s easy to get onto the track, hard to disengage. But the railroad isn’t at all frightening yet, it even has its appeal; all passengers are guaranteed an adventure, and a medal at the end.</p> <p>Later still, the horizon closes in yet further for Flaubert’s Emma Bovary, and comes to seem like a cage. Adventures lie on the other side and the longing becomes unbearable. Dreams and daydreams surge into the monotony of the quotidian. The lost infinitude of the outside world is replaced by the infinite expansion of the soul. The great illusion of the irreplaceable uniqueness of the individual—one of the sweetest of European illusions—blossoms forth.</p> <p>But the dream of the infinite expansion of the soul loses its magic when man is grasped by History (or what remains of it: the suprahuman force of an omnipotent society). History no longer beckons with the promise of a medal, but barely offers a surveyor’s job. What can K. do faced with the court or castle? Not a lot. Can’t he dream, at least, as Madame Bovary did before? No, the trap is too terrible and it sucks up all his thoughts and feelings—all he can think of is his trial, his surveying job. The infinite soul—if it ever existed—has become a more or less useless appendix.</p> <h3 id="5">5.</h3> <p>The path of the novel, over the last four centuries, has run parallel to the history of the Modern Era. Looked at in retrospect, it seems strangely short and limited. Isn’t that Don Quixote himself, disguised as a surveyor, returning to the village four hundred years later? He left long ago in search of adventures of his own choosing, but now in the village beneath the castle he has no choice. The adventure is laid down for him, it’s a petty squabble with the administration over a mistake in his dossier. So what has happened through four centuries to <em>adventure</em>, the first great subject of the novel? Has it become its own parody? Meaning what? That the path of the novel comes full circle to end in paradox?</p> <p>So it would seem. And that is by no means the only paradox. <em>The Good Soldier Schweik</em> is perhaps the last great comic novel. Isn’t it extraordinary that it is also a war story, with its action set in the army and on the front? What has happened to war and its horrors, when they become the subject of laughter?</p> <p>In Homer and in Tolstoy, war has a perfectly comprehensible meaning—Helen, or Russia, is what is being fought for. But Schweik and comrades go to the front without knowing why and—even more shockingly—without being interested in the reason why.</p> <p>What then is the motor of war if not Helen or the homeland? The will to power? That, surely, has lain behind all wars since the beginning of time. In Hasek’s book, though, the will to power is devoid of any serious argument. Nobody, not even the people who manufacture it, believes in the drivel put out by propaganda. The will to power, here, is naked, it is as naked as in Kafka’s novels where it shows itself in the incomprehensible machinations of the court and the castle. The court has no reason to hunt down K., just as the castle can draw no benefit from persecuting the surveyor K. Why did Germany, why does Russia today want to dominate the world? To be richer and happier, to have more wine, to have more sex? Not at all. The will to power is quite disinterested; it is unmotivated; it wills only its own will; it is pure irrationality.</p> <p>Kafka and Hasek thus bring us face to face with this enormous paradox: in the course of the Modern Era, Cartesian rationality has eaten away at all the values inherited from the Middle Ages. But at the very moment of the total victory of reason, pure irrationality (the will to power) suddenly dominates the world scene, because there is no longer any generally accepted value system that could block its path.</p> <p>This is what I should call a <em>terminal paradox</em>; it is the subject of one of the greatest European novels, Hermann Broch’s masterful <em>Sleepwalkers</em>.</p> <p>But there are other such terminal paradoxes: for example, the Modern Era has cherished a dream of humanity finding one day unity and everlasting peace out of the diversity of its separate civilizations. Today, at last, the history of the planet has become an indivisible whole, but unity is assured by everlasting, circulating war. World unity means: no escape, for anyone, anywhere.</p> <h3 id="6">6.</h3> <p>Husserl’s lectures on the European crisis and the possibility of the disappearance of European humanity were the philosopher’s last testament. He gave those lectures in the two capitals of central Europe. This coincidence has a deep meaning—for it was in that selfsame central part of Europe that the West first saw the death of the West, or, more exactly, the amputation of a part of itself, when Warsaw, Budapest, and Prague were swallowed up by the Russian empire. This catastrophe had a forerunner in the First World War, set in motion by the Hapsburg Empire, which led to the end of that empire and to a permanently unbalanced and weakened Europe.</p> <p>The time was past when man had only the monster of his own soul to grapple with—the peaceful time of Joyce and Proust. In the novels of Kafka, Hasek, Musil, Broch, the monster comes from outside and is called History, but it no longer has the aspect of the adventurer: it is inhuman, ungovernable, incalculable, unintelligible; and it is inescapable. That was the time (just after the First World War) when a constellation of great Central European novelists saw, felt, and grasped the terminal paradoxes of the Modern Era.</p> <p>But it would be wrong to read these novels as social and political prophecies, as if they were Orwellian anticipations. What Orwell has to tell us could have been said just as well (or rather, could be much better said) in an essay or pamphlet. The Central European novelists do the opposite and uncover (if I may again quote Broch) “what only the novel can uncover”: they demonstrate how, in the conditions of the terminal paradoxes, all existential categories suddenly change their meaning. What is <em>future</em> if the intellectuals of <em>The Man Without Qualities</em> have not the slightest suspicion that their lives will be swept away the next day by the Great War? What is <em>crime</em> if Broch’s Hugenau not only does not regret, but actually forgets the murder he has committed? And if the only great <em>comic</em> novel of the period, Hasek’s <em>Schweik</em>, has war as its subject, what then has happened to the comic? Where is the difference between public and private if K. is never without the two emissaries of the castle, even when making love? And in that case what is <em>solitude</em>?—a burden, an anxiety, a curse (as some would have us believe) or, on the contrary, the most precious value being suppressed by the ubiquitous collectivity?</p> <p>The periods of the novel’s history are very long (they have nothing to do with the feverish gyrations of fashion) and are identified by the particular aspect of being on which the novel concentrates. Thus the full potential of Flaubert’s discovery of the quotidian was only realized seventy years later, in James Joyce’s gigantic work. The period inaugurated fifty years ago by the constellation of Central European novelists (the period of terminal paradoxes) seems to me far from being ended.</p> <h3 id="7">7.</h3> <p>The end of the novel has been much discussed for a long time, notably by futurists, surrealists, the avant-garde generally. They saw the novel falling by the wayside of progress, on the road to a radically new future with an art bearing no resemblance to what had existed before. The novel was to be buried in the name of historical justice—like poverty, the ruling classes, obsolete automobiles, and top hats.</p> <p>But if Cervantes is the founder of the Modern Era, then the end of his inheritance ought to signify more than a mere stage in the history of literary forms: it should mean the end of the Modern Era. That is why those glibly pious obituaries of the novel seem frivolous to me—frivolous because I have seen and lived through the death of the novel, a violent death inflicted by bans, censorship, and ideological pressures in the world where I have spent much of my life and which is usually called totalitarian. It is then absolutely clear that the novel is mortal, as mortal as the Modern Era of the West. As a model of this Western world in the Modern Era, founded on the relativity and ambiguity of human affairs, the novel is incompatible with a totalitarian universe. This is a deeper incompatibility than that which separates a dissident from an <em>apparatchik</em>, or a civil rights campaigner from a torturer, because it is not just a matter of politics or morality, but an ontological difference. That means: a world based on a unique Truth is molded from a quite different substance from that of the relative and ambiguous world of the novel. Totalitarian Truth excludes relativity, doubt, questioning; it can never accommodate what I would call the wisdom of the novel.</p> <p>But aren’t there hundreds and thousands of novels published in huge editions and widely read in Communist Russia? Certainly; but these novels add nothing to the conquest of being. They uncover no new segment of existence; they only confirm what has already been said. And further: in confirming what has been said (by saying what has to be said) they fulfill their purpose, achieve their status, perform a useful service in the society that is theirs. By uncovering nothing, they fail to participate in the sequence of discoveries that for me constitutes the history of the novel. They place themselves beyond this history or, if you like, they are <em>novels from after the end of the history of the novel</em>.</p> <p>The history of the novel in Russia came to an end about fifty years ago. That was an event of huge importance, since the Russian novel had fascinated Europe for an entire century. Thus the death of the novel is not just an idea. It has already happened. And we now know <em>how</em> the novel dies. It doesn’t disappear; it falls outside its history. The novel dies quietly, unremarked, and no one gives so much as a whimper.</p> <h3 id="8">8.</h3> <p>Perhaps, though, the novel has been brought to the end of its road by the internal logic of its own development. Hasn’t it already exhausted all its possible fields of knowledge, all its possible forms?</p> <p>I’ve heard people compare the history of the novel to a seam of coal long since exhausted. But for me, it’s more like a mausoleum of missed opportunities and of misunderstood challenges. There are four challenges to which I respond especially:</p> <p><em>The challenge of play:</em> Sterne’s <em>Tristram Shandy</em> and Diderot’s <em>Jacques le fataliste</em> are for me the two greatest novelistic works of the eighteenth century. These two novels are playful on a grandiose scale and reach pinnacles of unseriousness never scaled before, or since. After Sterne and Diderot, the novel tied itself down to obligations of verisimilitude, realistic setting, and chronological order, and abandoned the seam opened up by these two masterpieces, which could have led to a different development of the novel (yes, an alternative history of the European novel can be imagined…).</p> <p><em>The challenge of dream:</em> The slumber of the imagination in the nineteenth-century novel was suddenly interrupted by Franz Kafka, who achieved what the surrealists subsequently called for but never themselves brought into being: the fusion of dream and reality. This was in fact a long-standing aesthetic ambition of the novel, intimated even as early as in Novalis, but its fulfillment required that special alchemy which only Kafka discovered. His enormous contribution should be understood less as the final step of a historical development than as an unexpected breach through which it can be seen that the novel is a place where the imagination can explode as in a dream, and that the novel can become “an other thing.”</p> <p><em>The challenge of thought:</em> Since Cervantes, the novel has tried to embody philosophical reflection. This tendency opens out completely in Musil and in Broch. If the novel is considered to be an “investigation of existence,” then the sense of this embodiment of philosophical reflection becomes clearer: it’s not a matter of supplementing science, of writing “polyhistory,” or of dealing with material not specific to the novel, but of mobilizing at the base of the narrative all the means that serve to illuminate man’s concrete being. It’s an enormous task to transform the novel into novelistic phenomenology and to find the artistic means of doing so. From that point of view the achievement of the two Viennese novelists—remarkable as it was—is but the first leg of a long journey.</p> <p><em>The challenge of time:</em> The period of terminal paradoxes incites the novelist to abandon the Proustian limits to the question of time (restricted to personal memory), and to broaden the problem to include the enigma of collective time, of European time: the enigma of a Europe looking back on its own past, weighing up its history like an old man seeing his whole past life in the glance of a single moment. Thus the strong temptation (which Günter Grass and Carlos Fuentes know well) to overstep the traditional restriction of the novel to the time-scale of a single life and to include several historical periods within a single work—which involves, of course, great changes in the novel’s form.</p> <p>But I don’t want to predict the future path of the novel, which I cannot know. I want only to arrive at this general conclusion: the disappearance of the novel, if it does happen, will not be due to exhaustion, but to its being in a world that is alien to it.</p> <h3 id="9">9.</h3> <p>The unification of world history, that humanitarian dream which a wry God has allowed to be fulfilled, has been accompanied by a process of dizzying reduction. True, the beetle of reduction has always gnawed away at the fabric of life—even the greatest love affair ends up as a hollowed lump of dead memories. But the character of modern society multiplies to a monstrous degree the effect of this curse: it reduces man’s life to its social function, the history of a people to a small set of events that are then themselves reduced to a tendentious interpretation; social life is reduced to political struggle, and that in turn is reduced to the confrontation of just two great global power blocs. Man is caught in a veritable whirlpool of reduction where Husserl’s “world of concrete living” is fatally obscured and where being is progressively forgotten.</p> <p>Now if the novel’s raison d’être is to keep the world of concrete living constantly before our eyes and to protect us from “the forgetting of being,” is it not necessary today more than ever that the novel should exist?</p> <p>That is how it seems to me. But alas, the novel too is eaten by the beetles of reduction, which diminish not only the sense of the world but also the meaning of works of art. Like all of culture, the novel is more and more in the hands of the mass media. As agents of the unification of world history, the media amplify and concentrate the process of reduction. They broadcast identical simplifications and stereotypes across the globe designed to be accepted by the greatest number, by everyone, by the whole of humanity. It doesn’t matter very much if different political interests are made evident by different organs of the media. Behind these surface differences reigns a common spirit. You have only to glance at American or European political weeklies of the left or right, from <em>Time to Der Spiegel</em>, to see that they all have the same view of life, reflected in the same ordering of the contents under the same headings, in identical forms of journalistic writing using the same vocabulary and the same style, in common artistic preferences, and in the identical ranking of things they find important or insignificant. The common spirit of the mass media, camouflaged by political diversity, is the spirit of our time. And this spirit seems to me to be contrary to the wisdom of the novel.</p> <p>The novel’s essence is complexity. Every novel says to the reader: “Things are not as simple as you think.” That is the novel’s eternal truth, but its voice grows ever fainter in a world based on easy, quick answers that come before and rule out the question. In this world, it’s either Anna or Karenin who is right, and the ancient wisdom of Cervantes, which speaks of the difficulty of knowing and of a truth that eludes the grasp, seems cumbersome and useless.</p> <p>The novel’s essence is continuity. Each work is an answer to preceding ones, each work contains all the anterior experience of the novel. But the spirit of our time is firmly focused on a present that is so expansive and full that it pushes the past over the horizon and reduces time to the present minute alone. Within this system the novel is no longer work (a thing made to last, to connect the past with the future) but an event among other current events, an inconsequential act, a mere gesture.</p> <h3 id="10">10.</h3> <p>Does this mean that the novel will disappear in a world “that is alien to it”? That it will abandon Europe in “the forgetting of being”? That only the endless verbiage of scribblers writing <em>novels after the end of the history of the novel</em> will remain? I’ve no idea. All I think I know is that the novel cannot live in peace with the spirit of our times: if it is to carry on uncovering the undiscovered, to continue “progressing” as novel, it can only do so against the “progress” of the world.</p> <p>The avant-garde saw things differently, for it was possessed by an ambition to be in harmony with the future. Avant-garde artists did indeed create courageous, difficult, provocative works that were condemned by the public, but they did so in the conviction that the <em>Zeitgeist</em> was with them, and would very soon accept them.</p> <p>Once upon a time I too thought that the future was the only competent judge of our actions. Later on I understood that running after the future is the worst conformism of all, a cowardly flattery of greater strength. For the future is always stronger than the present. It will judge us, to be sure—but without the slightest competence.</p> <p>But if the idea of progress arouses my suspicion, what are the values to which I feel attached? God? Fatherland? People? The Individual?</p> <p>My answer is as sincere as it is ridiculous: I am attached to nothing apart from the European novel, that unrecognized inheritance that comes to us from Cervantes.</p> <blockquote> <p>—Translated from the French by David Bellos</p> </blockquote> <p>July 19, 1984</p> <p><a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Milan_Kundera">Milan Kundera</a></p> <p>Milan Kundera (1929–2023) was born in Brno, Czechoslovakia. A lecturer in literature at FAMU, the Prague film academy, in the 1950s and 1960s he wrote three poetry collections and three plays before his first novel, <em>The Joke</em> (1967), brought him international acclaim after it was banned in Czechoslovakia following the 1968 Soviet invasion. Kundera emigrated to France in 1975, where he lived for the rest of his life, writing novels and essays in Czech and French. Among other honors, he was a recipient of the Jerusalem Prize, the Prix mondial Cino Del Duca, and the Franz Kafka Prize, and in 1983 astronomers at the Klet’ Observatory named an asteroid after him.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays"/><category term="language"/><category term="politics"/><category term="philosophy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A questioning of the death of questioning in novels, in dialogue with Heidegger.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Fireseed</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Fireseed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fireseed"/><published>2025-02-17T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-17T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Fireseed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Fireseed/"><![CDATA[<p><br/>Prometheus gave other beings fire. Conifers learnt to make cones for the pyre. Mycelia dwelt ‘neath cooking litter. Poppies slept waiting for ash to flower.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poems"/><category term="nature"/><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An ode to adaptation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Double R Diviner</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Double-R-Diviner/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Double R Diviner"/><published>2025-02-13T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-13T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Double%20R%20Diviner</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Double-R-Diviner/"><![CDATA[<p><br/> A Log Lady tends each stump in memory’s grove.<br/> Her narrow hands, stained cedar red, cast lots by phone.<br/> With burnt wood beside her, she awaits the Fates’ calls.<br/> Young Cassandra floats in, and old Sibyl reads palms.<br/> Paradise grows from gossip’s seed and prophecy.<br/> The seeress seeks out coffee, pie, and company.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poems"/><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For Margaret Lanterman (portrayed by Catherine E. Coulson), an American sibyl.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Harvey’s Justice, Nature &amp;amp; the Geography of Difference</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/2025-On-Harvey's-Justice,-Nature-&-the-Geography-of-Difference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Harvey’s Justice, Nature &amp;amp; the Geography of Difference"/><published>2025-02-11T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-11T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/2025-On%20Harvey&apos;s%20Justice,%20Nature%20&amp;%20the%20Geography%20of%20Difference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/2025-On-Harvey&apos;s-Justice,-Nature-&amp;-the-Geography-of-Difference/"><![CDATA[<p>In aggregate, the environmental issue “encompasses quite literally everything there is.” (Harvey 1996: 117). I am naive or all too ambitious for wanting to write about our natureculture(s). But nature is the phenomenological terrain; I feel it; we feel it. To treat the environment in a disembodied way, as abstract and lifeless – to make of our world “one vast gasoline station,” as Heidegger said – without a view to the future of our dwelling in <em>this</em> land, is unsustainable.</p> <p>David Harvey began his dialectical treatment of nature where systematic, (nonnative) American thinking about being-in-the-land began: Aldo Leopold’s <em>Sand County Almanac</em> (1949). He quoted:</p> <ul> We abuse land because we regard it as a commodity belonging to us. When we see land as a community to which we belong, we may begin to use it with love and respect. (Leopold) </ul> <p>Contra Marx:</p> <ul> Where money is not itself the community, it must dissolve the community. ... It is the elementary precondition of bourgeois society that labour should directly produce exchange value, i.e., money; and similarly that money should directly purchase labour, and therefore the labourer, but only insofar as he alienates his activity in exchange. ... Money thereby directly and simultaneously becomes <em>the real community</em>, since it is the general substance for the survival of all, and at the same time the social product of all. (Marx, *Grundrisse*, pp.224-6) </ul> <p>Weber and Sombart held that Judeo-Christian values led to capitalism, and thence, the domination of reason.[^1] Reason assumes that nature is there to be bound up by laws of production and conservation and motion. Today, scientific authority unbinds us. “Religion” comes perhaps from latin <em>religare</em> (to bind fast), which is also the etymological root of reliance – perhaps because gathering and relying on one another is our greatest virtue. Is not the strongest ideological defense of the free market that it binds together a society of producers in trade relations?<br/></p> <p>The hubris of it all is attractive. But market thinking leads to technical considerations of resource scarcity and optimizing welfare. It begs the Malthusian question, while it simultaneously justifies hoarding under the guise of free enterprise. Once we are in that mode of being-in-the-world, the question of how we <em>should</em> dwell within the land is an afterthought. We simply <em>must</em>, because we are in hock to rationers.<br/></p> <p>Marx had it that we make ourselves by transforming the world through labor, into exchange value, i.e., money. Keith Basso, in <em>Wisdom Sits in Places</em> (1996), instead suggested that we (really Western Apache tribespeople) make human nature by naming the moral landscape, by telling stories about it, and by being <em>within</em> it. Is naming the same thing as mastery? Adorno and the Frankfurt school made a problematic out of the mastery of nature, which is also the mastery of humankind. This led to a dialectic of internal drives and desires that we seem unable to escape. But Adorno tended to think about nature in terms of master and servant, and even in cultural aesthetics, he thought there should be an elite producing the art. Compare this with the dialectic of living in moral community that Basso constructed on behalf of his Apache fellows, whereby the stories they inscribe upon the land share wisdom across generations, helping wayward individuals to inwardly cultivate ethics of resilience and mental “smoothness.”<br/> (TBC)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reviews"/><category term="philosophy"/><category term="nature"/><category term="politics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In aggregate, the environmental issue “encompasses quite literally everything there is.” (Harvey 1996: 117). I am naive or all too ambitious for wanting to write about our natureculture(s). But nature is the phenomenological terrain; I feel it; we feel it. To treat the environment in a disembodied way, as abstract and lifeless – to make of our world “one vast gasoline station,” as Heidegger said – without a view to the future of our dwelling in this land, is unsustainable.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gather your wits, compatriots.</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Gather-your-wits,-compatriots/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gather your wits, compatriots."/><published>2025-02-08T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-08T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Gather%20your%20wits,%20compatriots</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Gather-your-wits,-compatriots/"><![CDATA[<p>Gather your wits, compatriots.<br/> “Riviera,” the hypocrite!<br/> America, O surrogate<br/> whose shame permits, and Justice quits.<br/><br/> Gather your wits, compatriots.<br/> From the river, a counterfeit,<br/> cruel lawgiver, will charge remit.<br/> The pact commits; follow its writs.<br/><br/> Gather your wits, compatriots.<br/> Progress has stalled, walled bit by bit.<br/> Grossly enthralled, we recommit.<br/> Ignore the twits. Our conscience splits.<br/><br/> Gather your wits, compatriots.<br/> To pick quarrels, what good does it?<br/> What of morals? Care not a whit?<br/> Heaven admits that it omits.<br/><br/> Gather your wits, compatriots,<br/> for Gaza’s fate our fate befits.<br/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflections"/><category term="poetry"/><category term="gaza"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A poem and a call to attention, because lament means nothing.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes from “Gaza, Our Oracle-Ruin”</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Notes-from-Gaza,-Our-Oracle-Ruin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes from “Gaza, Our Oracle-Ruin”"/><published>2025-02-05T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-05T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Notes%20from%20%22Gaza,%20Our%20Oracle-Ruin%22</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Notes-from-Gaza,-Our-Oracle-Ruin/"><![CDATA[<p>Hiba Abu Nada was a Palestinian poet killed at the age of 32 by an Israeli airstrike on her home in Khan Younis. She was a <em>shahiida</em> (شهيدة), not a martyr. The Arabic word for martyrdom is about witnessing, as all artists and poets do. Her death was not a considered sacrifice, although it may be considered such. She was a victim of genocide.</p> <p>I listened to Huda Fakhreddine read Abu Nada’s poem <a href="https://arablit.org/2023/12/04/our-loneliness-a-poem-by-hiba-abu-nada/">“Our Loneliness”</a> today:</p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: space-between;"> <div style="flex: 1; padding: 10px;"> How alone it was,<br/> our loneliness,<br/> when they won their wars.<br/><br/> Only you were left behind,<br/> naked,<br/> before this loneliness.<br/><br/> Darwish,<br/> no poetry could ever bring it back:<br/> what the lonely one has lost.<br/><br/> It’s another age of ignorance,<br/> our loneliness.<br/><br/> Damned be that which divided us<br/> then stands united<br/> at your funeral.<br/><br/> Now your land is auctioned<br/> and the world’s<br/> a free market.<br/><br/> It’s a barbaric era,<br/> our loneliness,<br/> one when none will stand up for us.<br/><br/> So, my country, wipe away your poems,<br/> the old and the new,<br/> and your tears,<br/> and pull yourself together. </div> <div style="text-align: center; flex: 1; padding: 10px;"> يا وحدنا<br/> ربح الجميع حروبهم<br/> وتُركت أنت أمام وحدك عاريًا<br/><br/> لا شعر يا درويش<br/> سوف يعيد ما خسر الوحيد وما فقد<br/><br/> يا وحدنا<br/> هذا زمان جاهلي آخر<br/> لُعن الذي في الحرب فرقنا به<br/> وعلى جنازتك اتحد<br/><br/> يا وحدنا<br/> الأرض سوق حرة<br/> وبلادك الكبرى مزاد معتمد<br/><br/> يا وحدنا<br/> هذا زمان جاهلي<br/> لن يساندنا أحد<br/><br/> يا وحدنا<br/> فامسح<br/> قصائدك القديمة والجديدة<br/> والبكاء<br/> وشدي حيلك يا بلد </div> </div> <p>If not for Fakhreddine’s reading, the poem and its context would have been lost on me. The closing «وشدي حيلك يا بلد» is translated here by Salma Harland as “my country… pull yourself together,” although I think it’s also like “gather your wits, compatriots.” The Egyptian singer and songwriter Mohammad Nouh made it a refrain in a song that became popular, first being played down by the Egyptian regime after the ‘67 loss against Israel, then being played up after the ‘73 loss-with-more-face-saved against Israel. Fakhreddine in her lecture rooted the sentiment of «شدي حيلك يا بلد» in an Arabic tradition of poetry that returns to pre-Islamic times, for example, to Samaw’al ibn ‘Adiya and Al-Shanfara, whose shared theme of self-sufficiency and willful loneliness still resonates today, especially in Palestine.</p> <p>This is why Fakhreddine said that “poetry takes history by the collar,” and that to understand poetry, both poem and reader must be liberated from the “extrapoetic.” Historians are given to the exercise of power, so it’s “safer to tune into the conversation of poets.” As a firm historicist, this idea challenges me. It turns on a notion of poetic timelessness that is strange to my American mind, and perhaps anyone who has lived in self-consciously revolutionary societies. Languages are living and not tools, Fakhreddine said, but does this not mean that their lifeways <em>must</em> change, even as the conversation continues? To take refuge in eternal, essential poetics is to hide from power. The first historians reap from us all anyway.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflections"/><category term="poetry"/><category term="gaza"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hereafter, we must begin from Gaza, even if things did not begin there.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">10+ avante-garde black metal albums</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/10+-avante-garde-black-metal-albums/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="10+ avante-garde black metal albums"/><published>2025-01-31T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/10+%20avante-garde%20black%20metal%20albums</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/10+-avante-garde-black-metal-albums/"><![CDATA[<p>Neglecting for now my love of doom, and death, and gothic, and stoner, and power, and prog, and various crossovers and *-cores, and especially post-metal, below is a list of 10 phenomenal albums in my formative subgenre: black metal. I work out to these and work out my emotions through them. They’re distinct from a first wave of thrash-inspired bands – exemplified by Bathory, whose <em>Under the Sign of the Black Mark</em> (1987) cleaved away something altogether new, and whose <em>Blood Fire Death</em> (1988) rooted various subgenres in norse myth. This has led to post-pagan meditations on time and place, and an atmospheric, environmental habit (at least in my preferred vein). Mayhem carried the torch back to Norway, where it set fire to churches, making a controversy of things. That was a thesis statement, while the antithesis is still being articulated. The synthesis lies on the horizon. My own selfish narrative begins in 1994, when both I and this decidedly avant-garde tradition of black metal were given form: <br/></p> <ol> <li><strong>Emperor</strong>, <em>In the Nightside Eclipse</em> (1994) – With respect to Bathory, this album bore the seeds that grew into the contemporary scene. One can hear in it the footfalls of the <em>jötnar</em>, wandering and sometimes sprinting across the frozen wastes.<br/>[Favorite track: “I Am the Black Wizards;” also Bathory cover “A Fine Day to Die”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Ulver</strong>, <em>Bergtatt - Et eeventyr i 5 capitler</em> (1995) – The earliest <em>gesamtkunstwerk</em> in the genre. This album offers a refined atmospheric sensibility, with powerful blasts, ethereal singing, acoustic interludes, and even a flute’s zephyr. Here’s to 30+ years of Ulver’s lycanthropy, and as many more moons as nature will allow.<br/>[Favorite track: “I Troldskog Faren Vild”]<br/></li> <li><strong>In The Woods…</strong>, <em>Heart of the Ages</em> (1995) – This album, I.t.W.’s first full-length, is eccentric and wonderful. Its varied instrumentation; wild, timeless motifs; female vocals; singing in English; and production quality put the band leagues ahead. I think they play this on repeat in Twin Peaks’ Black Lodge. It’s not as strong as <em>Bergtatt</em> but harmonizes with that album in its softer moments, making it a masterwork in its own right.<br/>[Favorite track: “The Divinity of Wisdom”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Paysage d’Hiver,</strong> <em>Paysage d’Hiver</em> (1999) – This demo by Swiss auteur Wintherr distorts recording technology, even as it transports listeners somewhere between Valhalla and Naströnd, or Fólkvangr and Helheim. Wintherr made everything we hear in it: a violin’s melody deadened by snow, synth dissipating into space, and the gathering storm of guitars and drums. Think William Basinski’s <em>The Disintegration Loops</em> (2002-3), but if rather than an evanescent time-capture of 9/11’s aftermath, it were a palimpsest of all European war.<br/>[Favorite track: “Welt aus Eis”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Agalloch</strong>, <em>The Mantle</em> (2002) – This masterpiece by Oregon’s greatest band is on my view the second wave’s culminating work of art. It was post-black metal before we knew it. Agalloch, named for عود (<em>oud</em>), that fragrant wood of the gods, imbued this album with the umbralight quality of pagan forestry. Words to describe it in English are lacking: <em>chiaroscuro</em>, <em>komorebi</em> (木漏れ日), <em>lichtung</em>.<br/>[Favorite track: “…And The Great Cold Death Of The Earth”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Drudkh</strong>, <em>Autumn Aurora</em> (2004) – Uniting Ukrainian (eco)poetics with a wonderfully articulated animism, this album is a kind of totem for me. I first listened to it while driving down through Colorado, with stark views of a lonely mountain; I hope to listen to it again someday when I visit <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pando_(tree)">Pando</a> in its Autumnal splendor.<br/>[Favorite track: “Sunwheel – Сонячне Коло”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Wolves In the Throne Room</strong>, <em>Diadem of 12 Stars</em> (2006) – This debut held a Cascadian candle to Europa’s torch, and the band has been, for me at least, the American scene’s leading lights ever since. The drumming somehow bridges aggressive shredding and thunderous dirges, while Jamie Myers’s guest vocals nurture this fragile offshoot of Olympia, WA’s iconoclastic scene.<br/>[Favorite track: “Queen of Borrowed Light”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Drautran</strong>, <em>Throne of the Depths</em> (2007) – Drautran’s debut and one-and-only. The instrumental compositions on this album are a cut above, with airy keyboards and eddying guitars, and the vocals are exceptionally far-ranging. Few others achieve this level of atmosphere.<br/>[Favorite track: “Gebaren Des Sterbens In Klanglosen Sphären”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Lunar Aurora</strong>, <em>Andacht</em> (2008) – Finally, a <em>gesamtkunstwerk</em> by German artists. This album uplifts the spirit, enveloping all of one’s senses, although it’s also quite grotesque. It embodies true beauty after the manner of Murnau’s, and Herzog’s, and lately, Eggers’s <em>Nosferatu</em>.<br/>[Favorite track: “Findling”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Aquilus</strong>, <em>Griseus</em> (2011) – Simply superb symphonic black metal. I can listen to this album back-to-back with Enya, which is how things should be: harmonious, interdependent, occasionally in syzygy. Let’s make it so.<br/>[Favorite track: “Loss”]<br/><br/><br/> <br/> 15 honorable mentions, for the sake of synergy:<br/> <ul> <li><strong>Master’s Hammer</strong>, <em>Ritual</em> (1991) – The vocals are awful, the pace meandering (as if over the Bohemian Massif), and still this album made a series of footnotes out of much of the second wave.</li> <li><strong>Mayhem</strong>, <em>De Mysteriis Dom Sathanas</em> (1994) – Vile. Mayhem’s best work is dissonance incarnate with lore to match. The title track/closer’s use of liturgical choruses rendered the satanic streak into a dialectic, finally.</li> <li><strong>Summoning</strong>, <em>Minas Morgul</em> (1995) – The finest LoTR-core. This albums is what Varg might’ve made had he a band and a higher appreciation of elvish craft.</li> <li><strong>Satyricon</strong>, <em>Nemesis Divina</em> (1996) – Satyricon composed the magnus opus of black metal <em>qua</em> music. Not overly sophisticated, in a sublime sense.</li> <li><strong>Nagelfar</strong>, <em>Hünengrab im Herbst</em> (1997) – Higher in production value than any prior album in the experimental vein, save <em>Nemesis Divina</em>, and in my opinion, the perfect precursor to the continental bloom of the aughts.</li> <li><strong>Sad Legend</strong>, <em>Sad Legend</em> (1998) – Hearing Naamah’s vocals on heartfelt opener <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Han_(cultural)">“Han”</a> makes me wonder how other metal artists could develop their own choral fidelity.</li> <li><strong>Windir</strong>, <em>1184</em> (2001) – This album was flawlessly executed. In many respects, I find it to be a harsher take on <em>Heart of the Ages</em>. RIP Valfar; <em>ars moriendi</em>.</li> <li><strong>Sigh</strong>, <em>Imaginary Soundscape</em> (2001) – It’s scary how clever this collection of songs is, by a troupe of Japanese black metal großmeister. <em>Imaginary Soundscape</em> projects familiarity with more genres than I care to name, mostly Western, which is why it’s offensive that the best aesthetic description I can mount in response is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b8MdhLepdUE">Jigoku</a>-<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OJgXU98lp8I">Kabuki</a> à la Nobu Nakagawa, in Gothic facepaint.</li> <li><strong>Negurǎ Bunget</strong>, <em>OM</em> (2006) – Intricate, progressive if not revolutionary, and rooted in the tradition despite its unusual sensibilities. Not a single other album I’ve listed is out of touch with <em>OM</em>, although Negurǎ Bunget dug deeper into other things.</li> <li><strong>Zuriaake</strong>, <em>Afterimage of Autumn</em> (2007) – A Chinese afterword on Drudkh’s <em>Autumn Aurora</em>, replete with classical instrumentation.</li> <li><strong>Blut Aus Nord</strong>, <em>Memoria Vetusta II – Dialogue With The Stars</em> (2009) – This album is a hopeless, empyrean epic. Climax “The Formless Sphere – Beyond the Reason” ceases all vocals in a triumphant end to man, beginning the title track’s denouement. The art of giving meaning to the void is human to no end.</li> <li><strong>Elderwind</strong>, <em>Волшебство живой природы / The Magic of Nature</em> (2012) – Purely atmospheric, a bit murky, and a favorite album of mine to play in the Adirondacks.</li> <li><strong>Batushka</strong>, <em>Литоургиiа (Litourgiya)</em> (2015) – The original eastern orthodox album resulted from an epiphany by creator Derph. Usurper Bart’s derivative band Patriarkh deserves profanity. In Derph’s words: “God’s hymns are more metal than any satanic black metal music out there.” Amen to that.</li> <li><strong>Mephorash</strong>, <em>Shem Ha Mephorash</em> (2019) – The most mature performance artists on the list. I didn’t understand what it meant for an album to be demanding until suffering (gladly) though <em>Shem Ha Mephorash</em>, a mystical experience of recurring motifs torn asunder.</li> <li><strong>Havukruunu</strong>, <em>Uinuos Syömein Sota</em> (2020) – The spirit of Scandinavian black metal went eastward, where Havukruunu’s crowning achievement was made (although each of their albums has been on the level). <em>Uinuos Syömein Sota</em> rings like a clear callback across the Gulf of Bothnia.<br/><br/> <br/> Next to listen to: Abduction, Abigor, Absu, Akitsa, Ascension, and that’s just A’s.<br/> Conspicuously absent: Burzum, Immortal, Marduk, Mgła, Taake <br/><br/> If you read to this point: Listen to more of this kind of music.<br/>If you’re a <em>fǫru-nautr</em> now wondering “Why the bias against the extreme wing?” – I have two ideas for you on our journey. First, beware unwittingly emulating that which you oppose. Second, negative aesthetics are nothing without beauty, a fact which has immediate consequences.<br/><br/> Stay tuned for more.</li> </ul> </li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="lists"/><category term="music"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Resonant ripples of the second wave. Here's a list of 10+ aesthetically experimental (post-)black metal albums, and one demo, I love. Yes, love.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An ode to soup</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/An-ode-to-soup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An ode to soup"/><published>2025-01-24T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-24T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/An%20ode%20to%20soup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/An-ode-to-soup/"><![CDATA[<p>Cabbage soup for the Russian soul:</p> <ul> «Щи да каша — пища наша»<br/> <em>(Shchi da kasha – pishcha nasha)</em><br/> Cabbage soup and porridge are our food.<br/> – Russian proverb<br/><br/> “It’s all the same to me. I should like cabbage soup and porridge better than anything; but of course there’s nothing like that here.”<br/> “<em>Porridge à la Russe</em>, your honor would like?” said the Tatar, bending down to Levin, like a nurse speaking to a child.<br/> “No, joking apart, whatever you choose is sure to be good. I’ve been skating, and I’m hungry. And don’t imagine,” he added, detecting a look of dissatisfaction on Oblonsky’s face, “that I shan’t appreciate your choice. I am fond of good things.”<br/> “I should hope so! After all, it’s one of the pleasures of life,” said Stepan Arkadyevitch. “Well, then, my friend, you give us two—or better say three—dozen oysters, clear soup with vegetables...”<br/><br/> <span href="https://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/1399/pg1399-images.html">– Leo Tolstoy, <em>Anna Karenina</em> (translation by Constance Garnett)</span> </ul> <p><br/> What is more universal than <em>soup</em>? One of my fondest memories: After a chilly UB football game, my dad took me to Scharf’s, a since-closed Schiller Park restaurant whose liver dumpling soup I would give anything to have again. Like wings, beef on weck, and sponge candy, lebernödelsuppe is a taste of home.</p> <p>Later, as an undergraduate, I attended a <a href="https://claiming.williams.edu/2015/03/13/special-event-stone-soup-what-is-the-taste-of-williams/">soup potluck</a> during cold Williamstown February. We shared a mess of pottage and read the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stone_Soup">pan-European folk tale about soup being made from a stone</a>. Now, I’m not fond of metaphors for making up a <em>fondant</em> culture. But I still have a soft spot for potluck <em>potage</em>.</p> <p>Cooking for myself, I prefer to make healthy meals with easily reheated leftovers. Soups are <a href="https://bushwickdaily.com/bushwick/perpetua-stew-bushwick-wikipedia-annie-rauwerda/">eternal</a> – the bones and peels and cores from one meal become a stock for the next. I currently cook two soups a week. Beside Pablo Neruda’s lovely poem about eel stew, I’ve listed below 10 soups I recently enjoyed: <br/></p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: space-between;"> <div style="flex: 1; padding: 10px;"> 1. <strong>Gulyásleves</strong> – paprika soup with bell pepper, beef, root vegetables, and egg noodles. I crave this heartily. <em>Mindennapi levesünk</em>, "our daily soup," is the Hungarian equivalent of "daily bread."<br/><br/> 2. <strong>Zuppa Toscana</strong> – sausage, potato, and kale soup. I make it frequently and like mine with sweet red pepper added.<br/><br/> 3. <strong>Pasta e Fagioli</strong> – ditalini and bean soup. I made red (tomato base), although <span href="https://www.angolalakesidemarket.com/">I grew up on white (vegetable broth/guanciale/parmesan base), with sausage added.</span> <br/><br/> 4. <strong>Minestrone</strong> – Italian soup with vegetables galore, and also some ditalini. It's often red, but I opted to make it <em>alla genovese</em>, with pesto.<br/><br/> 5. <strong>Jägertopf</strong> – hunter's stew, improvised with the meats available to me. I love turnips in this, while juniper berries and lingonberry preserves accentuate their sweetness. Tyrolese / Alpine wine is hard to find, so I cooked it down using Californian pinot noir. <br/><br/> 6. <strong>Kulajda</strong> – Czech mushroom soup, heavy on the dill. This is the first dish I've found that makes good use of dried (porcini) mushrooms.<br/><br/> 7. <strong>Borscht</strong> – beets, dill, and sour cream. I prefer beef borscht with broth made from scratch. Grating the beets always leaves my fingers ruddy. Once I even had a puréed beet-cream smoothie, served chilled at Barney Greengrass on the UWS. Sweet and perfect for summer.<br/><br/> 8. <strong>Solyanka</strong> – Russian anything-goes soup with pickles and olives/capers. I used kielbasa, but mushroom and cured fish versions entice me.<br/><br/> 9. <strong>Lohikeitto</strong> – Finnish salmon soup, with bunches of dill and a splash of lemon juice. I made this for Christmas day lunch, because it's light, and why not?<br/><br/> 10. <strong>Dopp i grytan</strong> – salty broth leftover from boiling the julskinka (Swedish Christmas ham). I love drinking it the day after Christmas. It tastes like culinary victory. <br/><br/><br/> Next for me: <br/><br/>Shchi (Russian cabbage soup), <br/>Zurek (Polish sour soup, or the Czech version with caraway added), <br/>honey carrot ginger soup, <br/>sauerkraut soup, <br/>Česnečka (Czech garlic soup), <br/>watercress soup, <br/>Bouillabaisse (Provençal fish stew), <br/>and of course, liver dumpling soup. </div> <div style="text-align: center; flex: 1; padding: 10px;"> <strong>Oda al caldillo de congrio</strong><br/> (<em>Ode to conger eel stew</em>)<br/> Pablo Neruda<br/> <br/> En el mar <br/> tormentoso <br/> de Chile <br/> vive el rosado congrio, <br/> gigante anguila <br/> de nevada carne. <br/> Y en las ollas <br/> chilenas, <br/> en la costa, <br/> nació el caldillo <br/> grávido y suculento, <br/> provechoso. <br/> Lleven a la cocina <br/> el congrio desollado, <br/> su piel manchada cede <br/> como un guante <br/> y al descubierto queda <br/> entonces <br/> el racimo del mar, <br/> el congrio tierno <br/> reluce <br/> ya desnudo, <br/> preparado <br/> para nuestro apetito. <br/> Ahora <br/> recoges <br/> ajos, <br/> acaricia primero <br/> ese marfil <br/> precioso, <br/> huele <br/> su fragancia iracunda, <br/> entonces <br/> deja el ajo picado <br/> caer con la cebolla <br/> y el tomate <br/> hasta que la cebolla <br/> tenga color de oro. <br/> Mientras tanto <br/> se cuecen <br/> con el vapor <br/> los regios <br/> camarones marinos <br/> y cuando ya llegaron <br/> a su punto, <br/> cuando cuajó el sabor <br/> en una salsa <br/> formada por el jugo <br/> del océano <br/> y por el agua clara <br/> que desprendió la luz de la cebolla, <br/> entonces <br/> que entre el congrio <br/> y se sumerja en gloria, <br/> que en la olla <br/> se aceite, <br/> se contraiga y se impregne. <br/> Ya sólo es necesario <br/> dejar en el manjar <br/> caer la crema <br/> como una rosa espesa, <br/> y al fuego <br/> lentamente <br/> entregar el tesoro <br/> hasta que en el caldillo <br/> se calienten <br/> las esencias de Chile, <br/> y a la mesa <br/> lleguen recién casados <br/> los sabores <br/> del mar y de la tierra <br/> para que en ese plato <br/> tú conozcas el cielo.<br/> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="lists"/><category term="cooking"/><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Soup-making is alchemy. These are my 10 favorite soups I've made so far this winter.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The business of firming, or forming?</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/The-business-of-firming,-or-forming/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The business of firming, or forming?"/><published>2025-01-22T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-22T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/The%20business%20of%20firming,%20or%20forming</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/The-business-of-firming,-or-forming/"><![CDATA[<p>Consider academics who affirm their identities, and who also confirm their biases. Next, consider academics who inform others in order to conform with them. While both firming and forming are intellectuals’ business, I’ve come down on the side of forming. A good poet innovates in form, while helping us conform to higher ideals. In other words, my ideal of language use privileges creative acts of (con)formation over replicative acts of confirmation.</p> <p>This identifies me with a kind of poetics shared by A. N. Whitehead and Richard Rorty. On one hand, I’m exasperated by fleeting arguments about metaphysics (Rorty), but on the other, metaphysical talk about enduring creations (Whitehead), such as rights, is self-evidently useful. Rorty’s critique[1] is still apt: The assertion that “there are rights,” could be redescribed as “under certain conditions we are disposed to say ‘there are rights,’ and that means…” The residue of Whitehead’s intuition after Rorty’s critique is an idea that it is in the business of times to change. So, we should make ourselves busy by changing things.</p> <p>David L. Hall helpfully clarified that Rorty and Whitehead began with different problematics.[2] Rorty wanted to solve an epistemological problem that results from having access to competing descriptive vocabularies. Hall wrote that “Whitehead’s problematic was how to characterize an intuition that, for a variety of reasons, had been marginalized in traditional philosophical discussion – namely, the intuition of flux and change.”[3]</p> <ul> That "all things flow" is the first vague generalization which the unsystematized, barely analyzed, intuition of men has produced... If we are able to go back to that ultimate, integral experience, unwarped by the sophistications of theory, that experience whose elucidation is the sole aim of philosophy, the flux of things is the one ultimate generalization around which we must weave our philosophic theory.<br/><br/>Alfred North Whitehead, <em>Process and Reality – an Essay in Cosmology</em> (The Free Press: 1978), 208. </ul> <p>The poet (<em>dichter</em>) and the philosopher (<em>denker</em>) do similar things. Rorty, for his “laissez-faire nominalism – his attempt to leave everything (except language) as it is – [was] forced to remain at the ‘meta’ level.”[4] He made everything of the poet and philosopher’s shared ability to change vocabularies and exchange metaphors. Whitehead was similarly disposed, but stricter in definition:</p> <ul> Philosophy is either self-evident or it is not philosophy... The aim of philosophy is sheer disclosure... (49)<br/> ... to find a conventional phraseology for the vivid suggestiveness of the poet... and thereby to produce a verbal symbolism manageable in other connections of thought (50).<br/><br/> Philosophy is akin to poetry... In each case there is reference to form beyond the direct meanings of words. Poetry allies itself to metre, philosophy to mathematical pattern. (174)<br/><br/> A. N. Whitehead, <em>Modes of Thought</em> (Macmillan 1938). </ul> <p>The difference between poetry and philosophy here is a matter of understanding, according to Hall’s interpretation of Whitehead. Poetry aids aesthetic understanding of the unrepeatable rhythms at a given time or place, while philosophy aids logical understanding of repeating, relational patterns. The distinction functions well enough.</p> <p>Rorty said that he attempted to “free Whitehead’s Category of the Ultimate (i.e., ‘Creativity’), not just from the theory of eternal objects, but from the fetters of a correspondence theory of truth, and from the idea that we need a super-science called metaphysics.”[5] His critics called him an anti-intellectual, regardless of their political leanings, because he reduced their shibboleths to favored words. This was due to his progressive, democratic philosophy. Poetry of the people, by the people, for the people – even if coincidence would determine what was actually read – would result in “a society that recognizes it is what it is… because certain poets and revolutionaries of the past spoke as they did.”[6] Human history is therefore “a long swelling, increasingly polyphonic poem that leads up to nothing save itself.”[7]</p> <p>I see here a similarity to Latour’s (1996) attempt to disabuse us of belief, to get us to stop believing in believing instead of doing. Rorty wrote: “If there really is an eternal fellow-sufferer who understands… so much the better, (but)… we can carry on perfectly well even if we suspect there is not.”[8] Hall wrote: “Socrates first advertised for our tradition that virtue is its own reward… But what if, as in the case of Socrates, one who believes that virtue is its own reward also has intimations of immortality? There’s the problem.”[9] We end up back near where I started – Rights are an example of the persistence of achieved value, and our metaphysical pretensions about rights are useful. Believing in rights does not maintain them, though. Action does. And verbal action, or poetry, does as well.</p> <p>Dewey gets the final word:</p> <ul> Peace in action not after it is the contribution of the ideal to conduct.<br/><br/> John Dewey, <em>Human Nature and Conduct</em> (Random House: 1957), 264. </ul> <p><br/><br/> [1] Richard Rorty, “The Subjectivist Principle and the Linguistic Turn,” in <em>Alfred North Whitehead – Essays on His Philosophy</em>, ed. George Kline (Prentice-Hall, 1963).</p> <p>[2] David L. Hall, “Whitehead, Rorty, and the Return of the Exiled Poets,” in <em>Whitehead’s Philosophy: Points of Connection</em>, ed. Janusz A. Polanowski and Donald W. Sherburne (SUNY Press, 2004).</p> <p>[3] <em>Ibid.,</em> 88.</p> <p>[4] <em>Ibid.</em>, 96.</p> <p>[5] Herman Saatkamp ed., <em>Rorty and Pragmatism – The Philosopher Responds to His Critics</em>, (Vanderbilt University Press: 1995), 34-35.</p> <p>[6] Rorty, <em>Contingency, Irony, Solidarity</em> (Cambridge University Press: 1989), 61.</p> <p>[7] Saatkamp ed., <em>Rorty and Pragmatism</em> (1995), 33.</p> <p>[8] <em>Ibid.,</em> 34.</p> <p>[9] Hall, “Whitehead, Rorty, and the Return of the Exiled Poets,” 99.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reviews"/><category term="language"/><category term="philosophy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some intellectuals are about affirming and confirming, others informing and conforming. I favor the latter, which is a project of using language to create a shared (conformal) experience.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Space vs. Place</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Space-vs.-Place/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Space vs. Place"/><published>2025-01-20T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-20T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Space%20vs.%20Place</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Space-vs.-Place/"><![CDATA[<p>I first came across the philosophical space/place distinction in a reference to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel_de_Certeau">Michel de Certeau’s</a> axiom, <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/2/2a/De_Certeau_Michel_The_Practice_of_Everyday_Life.pdf">translated from the French</a>: “Space is practiced place.” «L’espace est le lieu pratiqué.» (1984) While trying to locate the exact French phrase, I saw many examples of «le lieu» swapped for «l’espace». But in English I so often hear trite phrases like “safe space” and “sacred space,” and I know that cartesian space is a post-enlightenment invention. As another example, we have Saxon “instead of” and Norman “in lieu of,” both meaning in place of. So, while I think that de Certeau clearly made the correct distinction for European languages, it is odd to note how Eastern scholars like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arjun_Appadurai">Arjun Appadurai</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yi-Fu_Tuan">Yi-Fu Tuan</a> have flipped the space/place distinction, thereby making more of place than space.</p> <p>It could be arbitrary. Or, it could be cosmological. In the Germanic languages, we have obvious toponyms like Norwich, Hallstatt, Uppsala, Trondheim, etc. But the literal signification is nil. Only in “the old city” do we refer to hall and heim for directions. By contrast, when I lived in Jordan, I was told by an American expat to pay attention to landmarks, because the locals supposedly navigate by them in a way that we road-and-route trekkers do not. I found this to be true (although, maybe we were just lost and trying to understand a foreign place).</p> <p>Arjun Appadurai’s (1995) concept of the “production of locality” is about “transforming spaces into places” (<a href="https://www.upress.umn.edu/9780816627936/modernity-at-large/">1996, 183</a>). He explicitly credited de Certeau for making the distinction. I suppose a postcolonial geography inverts things.</p> <p>Yi-Fu Tuan, an influential “human geographer” (funny title imo), wrote a <a href="https://archive.org/details/spaceplaceperspe0000tuan/page/n7/mode/2up">1977 book</a> arguing that <a href="https://ls.wisc.edu/news/belonging-to-this-place-a-conversation-with-yi-fu-tuan/">place is space made meaningful</a>. While both Tuan and de Certeau’s books were published by UMinn Press, and while the latter doesn’t reference the former, because of the distinct English vs. French milieus I don’t think we have here a case of appropriation. Instead, what I see is Tuan the geographer taking space for granted, and de Certeau the Derridean deconstructionist doing the opposite.</p> <p>The Greek and Latin etymologies aren’t too helpful. Plateia (<em>πλατεία</em>) -&gt; piazza, plaza, platz, etc. <em>Spatium</em> -&gt; espacio, l’espace, and space. Space has been uniquely used to refer to timespans in English. But in Arabic, I don’t think the distinction is salient – مكان (makaan) refers to both space and place, and it comes from the root for being and entities. The related word كون refers to the universe, all of God’s creation, the geography of which might be less human and more divine than I’m used to. Overall, I’m left thinking that we all have peculiar ideas of locality.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflections"/><category term="language"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The space/place dichotomy is inverted by looking at it from East or West.]]></summary></entry></feed>