<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-09-24T18:50:12+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">JBall’s Site</title><subtitle>Jon Ball&apos;s personal site. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Fireseed</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Fireseed/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Fireseed"/><published>2025-02-17T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-17T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Fireseed</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Fireseed/"><![CDATA[<p><br/>Prometheus gave other beings fire. Conifers learnt to make cones for the pyre. Mycelia dwelt ‘neath cooking litter. Poppies slept waiting for ash to flower.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poems"/><category term="nature"/><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An ode to adaptation.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Double R Diviner</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Double-R-Diviner/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Double R Diviner"/><published>2025-02-13T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-13T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Double%20R%20Diviner</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Double-R-Diviner/"><![CDATA[<p><br/> A Log Lady tends each stump in memory’s grove.<br/> Her narrow hands, stained cedar red, cast lots by phone.<br/> With burnt wood beside her, she awaits the Fates’ calls.<br/> Young Cassandra floats in, and old Sibyl reads palms.<br/> Paradise grows from gossip’s seed and prophecy.<br/> The seeress seeks out coffee, pie, and company.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="poems"/><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[For Margaret Lanterman (portrayed by Catherine E. Coulson), an American sibyl.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">On Harvey’s Justice, Nature &amp;amp; the Geography of Difference</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/2025-On-Harvey's-Justice,-Nature-&-the-Geography-of-Difference/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="On Harvey’s Justice, Nature &amp;amp; the Geography of Difference"/><published>2025-02-11T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-11T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/2025-On%20Harvey&apos;s%20Justice,%20Nature%20&amp;%20the%20Geography%20of%20Difference</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/2025-On-Harvey&apos;s-Justice,-Nature-&amp;-the-Geography-of-Difference/"><![CDATA[<p>In aggregate, the environmental issue “encompasses quite literally everything there is.” (Harvey 1996: 117). I am naive or all too ambitious for wanting to write about our natureculture(s). But nature is the phenomenological terrain; I feel it; we feel it. To treat the environment in a disembodied way, as abstract and lifeless – to make of our world “one vast gasoline station,” as Heidegger said – without a view to the future of our dwelling in <em>this</em> land, is unsustainable.</p> <p>David Harvey began his dialectical treatment of nature where systematic, (nonnative) American thinking about being-in-the-land began: Aldo Leopold’s <em>Sand County Almanac</em> (1949). He quoted:</p> <ul> We abuse land because we regard it as a commodity belonging to us. When we see land as a community to which we belong, we may begin to use it with love and respect. (Leopold) </ul> <p>Contra Marx:</p> <ul> Where money is not itself the community, it must dissolve the community. ... It is the elementary precondition of bourgeois society that labour should directly produce exchange value, i.e., money; and similarly that money should directly purchase labour, and therefore the labourer, but only insofar as he alienates his activity in exchange. ... Money thereby directly and simultaneously becomes <em>the real community</em>, since it is the general substance for the survival of all, and at the same time the social product of all. (Marx, *Grundrisse*, pp.224-6) </ul> <p>Weber and Sombart held that Judeo-Christian values led to capitalism, and thence, the domination of reason.[^1] Reason assumes that nature is there to be bound up by laws of production and conservation and motion. Today, scientific authority unbinds us. “Religion” comes perhaps from latin <em>religare</em> (to bind fast), which is also the etymological root of reliance – perhaps because gathering and relying on one another is our greatest virtue. Is not the strongest ideological defense of the free market that it binds together a society of producers in trade relations?<br/></p> <p>The hubris of it all is attractive. But market thinking leads to technical considerations of resource scarcity and optimizing welfare. It begs the Malthusian question, while it simultaneously justifies hoarding under the guise of free enterprise. Once we are in that mode of being-in-the-world, the question of how we <em>should</em> dwell within the land is an afterthought. We simply <em>must</em>, because we are in hock to rationers.<br/></p> <p>Marx had it that we make ourselves by transforming the world through labor, into exchange value, i.e., money. Keith Basso, in <em>Wisdom Sits in Places</em> (1996), instead suggested that we (really Western Apache tribespeople) make human nature by naming the moral landscape, by telling stories about it, and by being <em>within</em> it. Is naming the same thing as mastery? Adorno and the Frankfurt school made a problematic out of the mastery of nature, which is also the mastery of humankind. This led to a dialectic of internal drives and desires that we seem unable to escape. But Adorno tended to think about nature in terms of master and servant, and even in cultural aesthetics, he thought there should be an elite producing the art. Compare this with the dialectic of living in moral community that Basso constructed on behalf of his Apache fellows, whereby the stories they inscribe upon the land share wisdom across generations, helping wayward individuals to inwardly cultivate ethics of resilience and mental “smoothness.”<br/> (TBC)</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reviews"/><category term="philosophy"/><category term="nature"/><category term="politics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In aggregate, the environmental issue “encompasses quite literally everything there is.” (Harvey 1996: 117). I am naive or all too ambitious for wanting to write about our natureculture(s). But nature is the phenomenological terrain; I feel it; we feel it. To treat the environment in a disembodied way, as abstract and lifeless – to make of our world “one vast gasoline station,” as Heidegger said – without a view to the future of our dwelling in this land, is unsustainable.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Gather your wits, compatriots.</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Gather-your-wits,-compatriots/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gather your wits, compatriots."/><published>2025-02-08T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-08T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Gather%20your%20wits,%20compatriots</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Gather-your-wits,-compatriots/"><![CDATA[<p>Gather your wits, compatriots.<br/> “Riviera,” the hypocrite!<br/> America, O surrogate<br/> whose shame permits, and Justice quits.<br/><br/> Gather your wits, compatriots.<br/> From the river, a counterfeit,<br/> cruel lawgiver, will charge remit.<br/> The pact commits; follow its writs.<br/><br/> Gather your wits, compatriots.<br/> Progress has stalled, walled bit by bit.<br/> Grossly enthralled, we recommit.<br/> Ignore the twits. Our conscience splits.<br/><br/> Gather your wits, compatriots.<br/> To pick quarrels, what good does it?<br/> What of morals? Care not a whit?<br/> Heaven admits that it omits.<br/><br/> Gather your wits, compatriots,<br/> for Gaza’s fate our fate befits.<br/></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflections"/><category term="poetry"/><category term="gaza"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A poem and a call to attention, because lament means nothing.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Notes from “Gaza, Our Oracle-Ruin”</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Notes-from-Gaza,-Our-Oracle-Ruin/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Notes from “Gaza, Our Oracle-Ruin”"/><published>2025-02-05T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-02-05T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Notes%20from%20%22Gaza,%20Our%20Oracle-Ruin%22</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Notes-from-Gaza,-Our-Oracle-Ruin/"><![CDATA[<p>Hiba Abu Nada was a Palestinian poet killed at the age of 32 by an Israeli airstrike on her home in Khan Younis. She was a <em>shahiida</em> (شهيدة), not a martyr. The Arabic word for martyrdom is about witnessing, as all artists and poets do. Her death was not a considered sacrifice, although it may be considered such. She was a victim of genocide.</p> <p>I listened to Huda Fakhreddine read Abu Nada’s poem <a href="https://arablit.org/2023/12/04/our-loneliness-a-poem-by-hiba-abu-nada/">“Our Loneliness”</a> today:</p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: space-between;"> <div style="flex: 1; padding: 10px;"> How alone it was,<br/> our loneliness,<br/> when they won their wars.<br/><br/> Only you were left behind,<br/> naked,<br/> before this loneliness.<br/><br/> Darwish,<br/> no poetry could ever bring it back:<br/> what the lonely one has lost.<br/><br/> It’s another age of ignorance,<br/> our loneliness.<br/><br/> Damned be that which divided us<br/> then stands united<br/> at your funeral.<br/><br/> Now your land is auctioned<br/> and the world’s<br/> a free market.<br/><br/> It’s a barbaric era,<br/> our loneliness,<br/> one when none will stand up for us.<br/><br/> So, my country, wipe away your poems,<br/> the old and the new,<br/> and your tears,<br/> and pull yourself together. </div> <div style="text-align: center; flex: 1; padding: 10px;"> يا وحدنا<br/> ربح الجميع حروبهم<br/> وتُركت أنت أمام وحدك عاريًا<br/><br/> لا شعر يا درويش<br/> سوف يعيد ما خسر الوحيد وما فقد<br/><br/> يا وحدنا<br/> هذا زمان جاهلي آخر<br/> لُعن الذي في الحرب فرقنا به<br/> وعلى جنازتك اتحد<br/><br/> يا وحدنا<br/> الأرض سوق حرة<br/> وبلادك الكبرى مزاد معتمد<br/><br/> يا وحدنا<br/> هذا زمان جاهلي<br/> لن يساندنا أحد<br/><br/> يا وحدنا<br/> فامسح<br/> قصائدك القديمة والجديدة<br/> والبكاء<br/> وشدي حيلك يا بلد </div> </div> <p>If not for Fakhreddine’s reading, the poem and its context would have been lost on me. The closing «وشدي حيلك يا بلد» is translated here by Salma Harland as “my country… pull yourself together,” although I think it’s also like “gather your wits, compatriots.” The Egyptian singer and songwriter Mohammad Nouh made it a refrain in a song that became popular, first being played down by the Egyptian regime after the ‘67 loss against Israel, then being played up after the ‘73 loss-with-more-face-saved against Israel. Fakhreddine in her lecture rooted the sentiment of «شدي حيلك يا بلد» in an Arabic tradition of poetry that returns to pre-Islamic times, for example, to Samaw’al ibn ‘Adiya and Al-Shanfara, whose shared theme of self-sufficiency and willful loneliness still resonates today, especially in Palestine.</p> <p>This is why Fakhreddine said that “poetry takes history by the collar,” and that to understand poetry, both poem and reader must be liberated from the “extrapoetic.” Historians are given to the exercise of power, so it’s “safer to tune into the conversation of poets.” As a firm historicist, this idea challenges me. It turns on a notion of poetic timelessness that is strange to my American mind, and perhaps anyone who has lived in self-consciously revolutionary societies. Languages are living and not tools, Fakhreddine said, but does this not mean that their lifeways <em>must</em> change, even as the conversation continues? To take refuge in eternal, essential poetics is to hide from power. The first historians reap from us all anyway.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflections"/><category term="poetry"/><category term="gaza"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Hereafter, we must begin from Gaza, even if things did not begin there.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">10+ avante-garde black metal albums</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/10+-avante-garde-black-metal-albums/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="10+ avante-garde black metal albums"/><published>2025-01-31T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-31T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/10+%20avante-garde%20black%20metal%20albums</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/10+-avante-garde-black-metal-albums/"><![CDATA[<p>Neglecting for now my love of doom, and death, and gothic, and stoner, and power, and prog, and various crossovers and *-cores, and especially post-metal, below is a list of 10 phenomenal albums in my formative subgenre: black metal. I work out to these and work out my emotions through them. They’re distinct from a first wave of thrash-inspired bands – exemplified by Bathory, whose <em>Under the Sign of the Black Mark</em> (1987) cleaved away something altogether new, and whose <em>Blood Fire Death</em> (1988) rooted various subgenres in norse myth. This has led to post-pagan meditations on time and place, and an atmospheric, environmental habit (at least in my preferred vein). Mayhem carried the torch back to Norway, where it set fire to churches, making a controversy of things. That was a thesis statement, while the antithesis is still being articulated. The synthesis lies on the horizon. My own selfish narrative begins in 1994, when both I and this decidedly avant-garde tradition of black metal were given form: <br/></p> <ol> <li><strong>Emperor</strong>, <em>In the Nightside Eclipse</em> (1994) – With respect to Bathory, this album bore the seeds that grew into the contemporary scene. One can hear in it the footfalls of the <em>jötnar</em>, wandering and sometimes sprinting across the frozen wastes.<br/>[Favorite track: “I Am the Black Wizards;” also Bathory cover “A Fine Day to Die”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Ulver</strong>, <em>Bergtatt - Et eeventyr i 5 capitler</em> (1995) – The earliest <em>gesamtkunstwerk</em> in the genre. This album offers a refined atmospheric sensibility, with powerful blasts, ethereal singing, acoustic interludes, and even a flute’s zephyr. Here’s to 30+ years of Ulver’s lycanthropy, and as many more moons as nature will allow.<br/>[Favorite track: “I Troldskog Faren Vild”]<br/></li> <li><strong>In The Woods…</strong>, <em>Heart of the Ages</em> (1995) – This album, I.t.W.’s first full-length, is eccentric and wonderful. Its varied instrumentation; wild, timeless motifs; female vocals; singing in English; and production quality put the band leagues ahead. I think they play this on repeat in Twin Peaks’ Black Lodge. It’s not as strong as <em>Bergtatt</em> but harmonizes with that album in its softer moments, making it a masterwork in its own right.<br/>[Favorite track: “The Divinity of Wisdom”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Paysage d’Hiver,</strong> <em>Paysage d’Hiver</em> (1999) – This demo by Swiss auteur Wintherr distorts recording technology, even as it transports listeners somewhere between Valhalla and Naströnd, or Fólkvangr and Helheim. Wintherr made everything we hear in it: a violin’s melody deadened by snow, synth dissipating into space, and the gathering storm of guitars and drums. Think William Basinski’s <em>The Disintegration Loops</em> (2002-3), but if rather than an evanescent time-capture of 9/11’s aftermath, it were a palimpsest of all European war.<br/>[Favorite track: “Welt aus Eis”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Agalloch</strong>, <em>The Mantle</em> (2002) – This masterpiece by Oregon’s greatest band is on my view the second wave’s culminating work of art. It was post-black metal before we knew it. Agalloch, named for عود (<em>oud</em>), that fragrant wood of the gods, imbued this album with the umbralight quality of pagan forestry. Words to describe it in English are lacking: <em>chiaroscuro</em>, <em>komorebi</em> (木漏れ日), <em>lichtung</em>.<br/>[Favorite track: “…And The Great Cold Death Of The Earth”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Drudkh</strong>, <em>Autumn Aurora</em> (2004) – Uniting Ukrainian (eco)poetics with a wonderfully articulated animism, this album is a kind of totem for me. I first listened to it while driving down through Colorado, with stark views of a lonely mountain; I hope to listen to it again someday when I visit <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Pando_(tree)">Pando</a> in its Autumnal splendor.<br/>[Favorite track: “Sunwheel – Сонячне Коло”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Wolves In the Throne Room</strong>, <em>Diadem of 12 Stars</em> (2006) – This debut held a Cascadian candle to Europa’s torch, and the band has been, for me at least, the American scene’s leading lights ever since. The drumming somehow bridges aggressive shredding and thunderous dirges, while Jamie Myers’s guest vocals nurture this fragile offshoot of Olympia, WA’s iconoclastic scene.<br/>[Favorite track: “Queen of Borrowed Light”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Drautran</strong>, <em>Throne of the Depths</em> (2007) – Drautran’s debut and one-and-only. The instrumental compositions on this album are a cut above, with airy keyboards and eddying guitars, and the vocals are exceptionally far-ranging. Few others achieve this level of atmosphere.<br/>[Favorite track: “Gebaren Des Sterbens In Klanglosen Sphären”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Lunar Aurora</strong>, <em>Andacht</em> (2008) – Finally, a <em>gesamtkunstwerk</em> by German artists. This album uplifts the spirit, enveloping all of one’s senses, although it’s also quite grotesque. It embodies true beauty after the manner of Murnau’s, and Herzog’s, and lately, Eggers’s <em>Nosferatu</em>.<br/>[Favorite track: “Findling”]<br/></li> <li><strong>Aquilus</strong>, <em>Griseus</em> (2011) – Simply superb symphonic black metal. I can listen to this album back-to-back with Enya, which is how things should be: harmonious, interdependent, occasionally in syzygy. Let’s make it so.<br/>[Favorite track: “Loss”]<br/><br/><br/> <br/> 15 honorable mentions, for the sake of synergy:<br/> <ul> <li><strong>Master’s Hammer</strong>, <em>Ritual</em> (1991) – The vocals are awful, the pace meandering (as if over the Bohemian Massif), and still this album made a series of footnotes out of much of the second wave.</li> <li><strong>Mayhem</strong>, <em>De Mysteriis Dom Sathanas</em> (1994) – Vile. Mayhem’s best work is dissonance incarnate with lore to match. The title track/closer’s use of liturgical choruses rendered the satanic streak into a dialectic, finally.</li> <li><strong>Summoning</strong>, <em>Minas Morgul</em> (1995) – The finest LoTR-core. This albums is what Varg might’ve made had he a band and a higher appreciation of elvish craft.</li> <li><strong>Satyricon</strong>, <em>Nemesis Divina</em> (1996) – Satyricon composed the magnus opus of black metal <em>qua</em> music. Not overly sophisticated, in a sublime sense.</li> <li><strong>Nagelfar</strong>, <em>Hünengrab im Herbst</em> (1997) – Higher in production value than any prior album in the experimental vein, save <em>Nemesis Divina</em>, and in my opinion, the perfect precursor to the continental bloom of the aughts.</li> <li><strong>Sad Legend</strong>, <em>Sad Legend</em> (1998) – Hearing Naamah’s vocals on heartfelt opener <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Han_(cultural)">“Han”</a> makes me wonder how other metal artists could develop their own choral fidelity.</li> <li><strong>Windir</strong>, <em>1184</em> (2001) – This album was flawlessly executed. In many respects, I find it to be a harsher take on <em>Heart of the Ages</em>. RIP Valfar; <em>ars moriendi</em>.</li> <li><strong>Sigh</strong>, <em>Imaginary Soundscape</em> (2001) – It’s scary how clever this collection of songs is, by a troupe of Japanese black metal großmeister. <em>Imaginary Soundscape</em> projects familiarity with more genres than I care to name, mostly Western, which is why it’s offensive that the best aesthetic description I can mount in response is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=b8MdhLepdUE">Jigoku</a>-<a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=OJgXU98lp8I">Kabuki</a> à la Nobu Nakagawa, in Gothic facepaint.</li> <li><strong>Negurǎ Bunget</strong>, <em>OM</em> (2006) – Intricate, progressive if not revolutionary, and rooted in the tradition despite its unusual sensibilities. Not a single other album I’ve listed is out of touch with <em>OM</em>, although Negurǎ Bunget dug deeper into other things.</li> <li><strong>Zuriaake</strong>, <em>Afterimage of Autumn</em> (2007) – A Chinese afterword on Drudkh’s <em>Autumn Aurora</em>, replete with classical instrumentation.</li> <li><strong>Blut Aus Nord</strong>, <em>Memoria Vetusta II – Dialogue With The Stars</em> (2009) – This album is a hopeless, empyrean epic. Climax “The Formless Sphere – Beyond the Reason” ceases all vocals in a triumphant end to man, beginning the title track’s denouement. The art of giving meaning to the void is human to no end.</li> <li><strong>Elderwind</strong>, <em>Волшебство живой природы / The Magic of Nature</em> (2012) – Purely atmospheric, a bit murky, and a favorite album of mine to play in the Adirondacks.</li> <li><strong>Batushka</strong>, <em>Литоургиiа (Litourgiya)</em> (2015) – The original eastern orthodox album resulted from an epiphany by creator Derph. Usurper Bart’s derivative band Patriarkh deserves profanity. In Derph’s words: “God’s hymns are more metal than any satanic black metal music out there.” Amen to that.</li> <li><strong>Mephorash</strong>, <em>Shem Ha Mephorash</em> (2019) – The most mature performance artists on the list. I didn’t understand what it meant for an album to be demanding until suffering (gladly) though <em>Shem Ha Mephorash</em>, a mystical experience of recurring motifs torn asunder.</li> <li><strong>Havukruunu</strong>, <em>Uinuos Syömein Sota</em> (2020) – The spirit of Scandinavian black metal went eastward, where Havukruunu’s crowning achievement was made (although each of their albums has been on the level). <em>Uinuos Syömein Sota</em> rings like a clear callback across the Gulf of Bothnia.<br/><br/> <br/> Next to listen to: Abduction, Abigor, Absu, Akitsa, Ascension, and that’s just A’s.<br/> Conspicuously absent: Burzum, Immortal, Marduk, Mgła, Taake <br/><br/> If you read to this point: Listen to more of this kind of music.<br/>If you’re a <em>fǫru-nautr</em> now wondering “Why the bias against the extreme wing?” – I have two ideas for you on our journey. First, beware unwittingly emulating that which you oppose. Second, negative aesthetics are nothing without beauty, a fact which has immediate consequences.<br/><br/> Stay tuned for more.</li> </ul> </li> </ol>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="lists"/><category term="music"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Resonant ripples of the second wave. Here's a list of 10+ aesthetically experimental (post-)black metal albums, and one demo, I love. Yes, love.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">An ode to soup</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/An-ode-to-soup/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="An ode to soup"/><published>2025-01-24T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-24T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/An%20ode%20to%20soup</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/An-ode-to-soup/"><![CDATA[<p>Cabbage soup for the Russian soul:</p> <ul> «Щи да каша — пища наша»<br/> <em>(Shchi da kasha – pishcha nasha)</em><br/> Cabbage soup and porridge are our food.<br/> – Russian proverb<br/><br/> “It’s all the same to me. I should like cabbage soup and porridge better than anything; but of course there’s nothing like that here.”<br/> “<em>Porridge à la Russe</em>, your honor would like?” said the Tatar, bending down to Levin, like a nurse speaking to a child.<br/> “No, joking apart, whatever you choose is sure to be good. I’ve been skating, and I’m hungry. And don’t imagine,” he added, detecting a look of dissatisfaction on Oblonsky’s face, “that I shan’t appreciate your choice. I am fond of good things.”<br/> “I should hope so! After all, it’s one of the pleasures of life,” said Stepan Arkadyevitch. “Well, then, my friend, you give us two—or better say three—dozen oysters, clear soup with vegetables...”<br/><br/> <span href="https://www.gutenberg.org/cache/epub/1399/pg1399-images.html">– Leo Tolstoy, <em>Anna Karenina</em> (translation by Constance Garnett)</span> </ul> <p><br/> What is more universal than <em>soup</em>? One of my fondest memories: After a chilly UB football game, my dad took me to Scharf’s, a since-closed Schiller Park restaurant whose liver dumpling soup I would give anything to have again. Like wings, beef on weck, and sponge candy, lebernödelsuppe is a taste of home.</p> <p>Later, as an undergraduate, I attended a <a href="https://claiming.williams.edu/2015/03/13/special-event-stone-soup-what-is-the-taste-of-williams/">soup potluck</a> during cold Williamstown February. We shared a mess of pottage and read the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stone_Soup">pan-European folk tale about soup being made from a stone</a>. Now, I’m not fond of metaphors for making up a <em>fondant</em> culture. But I still have a soft spot for potluck <em>potage</em>.</p> <p>Cooking for myself, I prefer to make healthy meals with easily reheated leftovers. Soups are <a href="https://bushwickdaily.com/bushwick/perpetua-stew-bushwick-wikipedia-annie-rauwerda/">eternal</a> – the bones and peels and cores from one meal become a stock for the next. I currently cook two soups a week. Beside Pablo Neruda’s lovely poem about eel stew, I’ve listed below 10 soups I recently enjoyed: <br/></p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: space-between;"> <div style="flex: 1; padding: 10px;"> 1. <strong>Gulyásleves</strong> – paprika soup with bell pepper, beef, root vegetables, and egg noodles. I crave this heartily. <em>Mindennapi levesünk</em>, "our daily soup," is the Hungarian equivalent of "daily bread."<br/><br/> 2. <strong>Zuppa Toscana</strong> – sausage, potato, and kale soup. I make it frequently and like mine with sweet red pepper added.<br/><br/> 3. <strong>Pasta e Fagioli</strong> – ditalini and bean soup. I made red (tomato base), although <span href="https://www.angolalakesidemarket.com/">I grew up on white (vegetable broth/guanciale/parmesan base), with sausage added.</span> <br/><br/> 4. <strong>Minestrone</strong> – Italian soup with vegetables galore, and also some ditalini. It's often red, but I opted to make it <em>alla genovese</em>, with pesto.<br/><br/> 5. <strong>Jägertopf</strong> – hunter's stew, improvised with the meats available to me. I love turnips in this, while juniper berries and lingonberry preserves accentuate their sweetness. Tyrolese / Alpine wine is hard to find, so I cooked it down using Californian pinot noir. <br/><br/> 6. <strong>Kulajda</strong> – Czech mushroom soup, heavy on the dill. This is the first dish I've found that makes good use of dried (porcini) mushrooms.<br/><br/> 7. <strong>Borscht</strong> – beets, dill, and sour cream. I prefer beef borscht with broth made from scratch. Grating the beets always leaves my fingers ruddy. Once I even had a puréed beet-cream smoothie, served chilled at Barney Greengrass on the UWS. Sweet and perfect for summer.<br/><br/> 8. <strong>Solyanka</strong> – Russian anything-goes soup with pickles and olives/capers. I used kielbasa, but mushroom and cured fish versions entice me.<br/><br/> 9. <strong>Lohikeitto</strong> – Finnish salmon soup, with bunches of dill and a splash of lemon juice. I made this for Christmas day lunch, because it's light, and why not?<br/><br/> 10. <strong>Dopp i grytan</strong> – salty broth leftover from boiling the julskinka (Swedish Christmas ham). I love drinking it the day after Christmas. It tastes like culinary victory. <br/><br/><br/> Next for me: <br/><br/>Shchi (Russian cabbage soup), <br/>Zurek (Polish sour soup, or the Czech version with caraway added), <br/>honey carrot ginger soup, <br/>sauerkraut soup, <br/>Česnečka (Czech garlic soup), <br/>watercress soup, <br/>Bouillabaisse (Provençal fish stew), <br/>and of course, liver dumpling soup. </div> <div style="text-align: center; flex: 1; padding: 10px;"> <strong>Oda al caldillo de congrio</strong><br/> (<em>Ode to conger eel stew</em>)<br/> Pablo Neruda<br/> <br/> En el mar <br/> tormentoso <br/> de Chile <br/> vive el rosado congrio, <br/> gigante anguila <br/> de nevada carne. <br/> Y en las ollas <br/> chilenas, <br/> en la costa, <br/> nació el caldillo <br/> grávido y suculento, <br/> provechoso. <br/> Lleven a la cocina <br/> el congrio desollado, <br/> su piel manchada cede <br/> como un guante <br/> y al descubierto queda <br/> entonces <br/> el racimo del mar, <br/> el congrio tierno <br/> reluce <br/> ya desnudo, <br/> preparado <br/> para nuestro apetito. <br/> Ahora <br/> recoges <br/> ajos, <br/> acaricia primero <br/> ese marfil <br/> precioso, <br/> huele <br/> su fragancia iracunda, <br/> entonces <br/> deja el ajo picado <br/> caer con la cebolla <br/> y el tomate <br/> hasta que la cebolla <br/> tenga color de oro. <br/> Mientras tanto <br/> se cuecen <br/> con el vapor <br/> los regios <br/> camarones marinos <br/> y cuando ya llegaron <br/> a su punto, <br/> cuando cuajó el sabor <br/> en una salsa <br/> formada por el jugo <br/> del océano <br/> y por el agua clara <br/> que desprendió la luz de la cebolla, <br/> entonces <br/> que entre el congrio <br/> y se sumerja en gloria, <br/> que en la olla <br/> se aceite, <br/> se contraiga y se impregne. <br/> Ya sólo es necesario <br/> dejar en el manjar <br/> caer la crema <br/> como una rosa espesa, <br/> y al fuego <br/> lentamente <br/> entregar el tesoro <br/> hasta que en el caldillo <br/> se calienten <br/> las esencias de Chile, <br/> y a la mesa <br/> lleguen recién casados <br/> los sabores <br/> del mar y de la tierra <br/> para que en ese plato <br/> tú conozcas el cielo.<br/> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="lists"/><category term="cooking"/><category term="poetry"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Soup-making is alchemy. These are my 10 favorite soups I've made so far this winter.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The business of firming, or forming?</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/The-business-of-firming,-or-forming/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The business of firming, or forming?"/><published>2025-01-22T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-22T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/The%20business%20of%20firming,%20or%20forming</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/The-business-of-firming,-or-forming/"><![CDATA[<p>Consider academics who affirm their identities, and who also confirm their biases. Next, consider academics who inform others in order to conform with them. While both firming and forming are intellectuals’ business, I’ve come down on the side of forming. A good poet innovates in form, while helping us conform to higher ideals. In other words, my ideal of language use privileges creative acts of (con)formation over replicative acts of confirmation.</p> <p>This identifies me with a kind of poetics shared by A. N. Whitehead and Richard Rorty. On one hand, I’m exasperated by fleeting arguments about metaphysics (Rorty), but on the other, metaphysical talk about enduring creations (Whitehead), such as rights, is self-evidently useful. Rorty’s critique[1] is still apt: The assertion that “there are rights,” could be redescribed as “under certain conditions we are disposed to say ‘there are rights,’ and that means…” The residue of Whitehead’s intuition after Rorty’s critique is an idea that it is in the business of times to change. So, we should make ourselves busy by changing things.</p> <p>David L. Hall helpfully clarified that Rorty and Whitehead began with different problematics.[2] Rorty wanted to solve an epistemological problem that results from having access to competing descriptive vocabularies. Hall wrote that “Whitehead’s problematic was how to characterize an intuition that, for a variety of reasons, had been marginalized in traditional philosophical discussion – namely, the intuition of flux and change.”[3]</p> <ul> That "all things flow" is the first vague generalization which the unsystematized, barely analyzed, intuition of men has produced... If we are able to go back to that ultimate, integral experience, unwarped by the sophistications of theory, that experience whose elucidation is the sole aim of philosophy, the flux of things is the one ultimate generalization around which we must weave our philosophic theory.<br/><br/>Alfred North Whitehead, <em>Process and Reality – an Essay in Cosmology</em> (The Free Press: 1978), 208. </ul> <p>The poet (<em>dichter</em>) and the philosopher (<em>denker</em>) do similar things. Rorty, for his “laissez-faire nominalism – his attempt to leave everything (except language) as it is – [was] forced to remain at the ‘meta’ level.”[4] He made everything of the poet and philosopher’s shared ability to change vocabularies and exchange metaphors. Whitehead was similarly disposed, but stricter in definition:</p> <ul> Philosophy is either self-evident or it is not philosophy... The aim of philosophy is sheer disclosure... (49)<br/> ... to find a conventional phraseology for the vivid suggestiveness of the poet... and thereby to produce a verbal symbolism manageable in other connections of thought (50).<br/><br/> Philosophy is akin to poetry... In each case there is reference to form beyond the direct meanings of words. Poetry allies itself to metre, philosophy to mathematical pattern. (174)<br/><br/> A. N. Whitehead, <em>Modes of Thought</em> (Macmillan 1938). </ul> <p>The difference between poetry and philosophy here is a matter of understanding, according to Hall’s interpretation of Whitehead. Poetry aids aesthetic understanding of the unrepeatable rhythms at a given time or place, while philosophy aids logical understanding of repeating, relational patterns. The distinction functions well enough.</p> <p>Rorty said that he attempted to “free Whitehead’s Category of the Ultimate (i.e., ‘Creativity’), not just from the theory of eternal objects, but from the fetters of a correspondence theory of truth, and from the idea that we need a super-science called metaphysics.”[5] His critics called him an anti-intellectual, regardless of their political leanings, because he reduced their shibboleths to favored words. This was due to his progressive, democratic philosophy. Poetry of the people, by the people, for the people – even if coincidence would determine what was actually read – would result in “a society that recognizes it is what it is… because certain poets and revolutionaries of the past spoke as they did.”[6] Human history is therefore “a long swelling, increasingly polyphonic poem that leads up to nothing save itself.”[7]</p> <p>I see here a similarity to Latour’s (1996) attempt to disabuse us of belief, to get us to stop believing in believing instead of doing. Rorty wrote: “If there really is an eternal fellow-sufferer who understands… so much the better, (but)… we can carry on perfectly well even if we suspect there is not.”[8] Hall wrote: “Socrates first advertised for our tradition that virtue is its own reward… But what if, as in the case of Socrates, one who believes that virtue is its own reward also has intimations of immortality? There’s the problem.”[9] We end up back near where I started – Rights are an example of the persistence of achieved value, and our metaphysical pretensions about rights are useful. Believing in rights does not maintain them, though. Action does. And verbal action, or poetry, does as well.</p> <p>Dewey gets the final word:</p> <ul> Peace in action not after it is the contribution of the ideal to conduct.<br/><br/> John Dewey, <em>Human Nature and Conduct</em> (Random House: 1957), 264. </ul> <p><br/><br/> [1] Richard Rorty, “The Subjectivist Principle and the Linguistic Turn,” in <em>Alfred North Whitehead – Essays on His Philosophy</em>, ed. George Kline (Prentice-Hall, 1963).</p> <p>[2] David L. Hall, “Whitehead, Rorty, and the Return of the Exiled Poets,” in <em>Whitehead’s Philosophy: Points of Connection</em>, ed. Janusz A. Polanowski and Donald W. Sherburne (SUNY Press, 2004).</p> <p>[3] <em>Ibid.,</em> 88.</p> <p>[4] <em>Ibid.</em>, 96.</p> <p>[5] Herman Saatkamp ed., <em>Rorty and Pragmatism – The Philosopher Responds to His Critics</em>, (Vanderbilt University Press: 1995), 34-35.</p> <p>[6] Rorty, <em>Contingency, Irony, Solidarity</em> (Cambridge University Press: 1989), 61.</p> <p>[7] Saatkamp ed., <em>Rorty and Pragmatism</em> (1995), 33.</p> <p>[8] <em>Ibid.,</em> 34.</p> <p>[9] Hall, “Whitehead, Rorty, and the Return of the Exiled Poets,” 99.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reviews"/><category term="language"/><category term="philosophy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Some intellectuals are about affirming and confirming, others informing and conforming. I favor the latter, which is a project of using language to create a shared (conformal) experience.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Space vs. Place</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Space-vs.-Place/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Space vs. Place"/><published>2025-01-20T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-20T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Space%20vs.%20Place</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Space-vs.-Place/"><![CDATA[<p>I first came across the philosophical space/place distinction in a reference to <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Michel_de_Certeau">Michel de Certeau’s</a> axiom, <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/2/2a/De_Certeau_Michel_The_Practice_of_Everyday_Life.pdf">translated from the French</a>: “Space is practiced place.” «L’espace est le lieu pratiqué.» (1984) While trying to locate the exact French phrase, I saw many examples of «le lieu» swapped for «l’espace». But in English I so often hear trite phrases like “safe space” and “sacred space,” and I know that cartesian space is a post-enlightenment invention. As another example, we have Saxon “instead of” and Norman “in lieu of,” both meaning in place of. So, while I think that de Certeau clearly made the correct distinction for European languages, it is odd to note how Eastern scholars like <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arjun_Appadurai">Arjun Appadurai</a> and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Yi-Fu_Tuan">Yi-Fu Tuan</a> have flipped the space/place distinction, thereby making more of place than space.</p> <p>It could be arbitrary. Or, it could be cosmological. In the Germanic languages, we have obvious toponyms like Norwich, Hallstatt, Uppsala, Trondheim, etc. But the literal signification is nil. Only in “the old city” do we refer to hall and heim for directions. By contrast, when I lived in Jordan, I was told by an American expat to pay attention to landmarks, because the locals supposedly navigate by them in a way that we road-and-route trekkers do not. I found this to be true (although, maybe we were just lost and trying to understand a foreign place).</p> <p>Arjun Appadurai’s (1995) concept of the “production of locality” is about “transforming spaces into places” (<a href="https://www.upress.umn.edu/9780816627936/modernity-at-large/">1996, 183</a>). He explicitly credited de Certeau for making the distinction. I suppose a postcolonial geography inverts things.</p> <p>Yi-Fu Tuan, an influential “human geographer” (funny title imo), wrote a <a href="https://archive.org/details/spaceplaceperspe0000tuan/page/n7/mode/2up">1977 book</a> arguing that <a href="https://ls.wisc.edu/news/belonging-to-this-place-a-conversation-with-yi-fu-tuan/">place is space made meaningful</a>. While both Tuan and de Certeau’s books were published by UMinn Press, and while the latter doesn’t reference the former, because of the distinct English vs. French milieus I don’t think we have here a case of appropriation. Instead, what I see is Tuan the geographer taking space for granted, and de Certeau the Derridean deconstructionist doing the opposite.</p> <p>The Greek and Latin etymologies aren’t too helpful. Plateia (<em>πλατεία</em>) -&gt; piazza, plaza, platz, etc. <em>Spatium</em> -&gt; espacio, l’espace, and space. Space has been uniquely used to refer to timespans in English. But in Arabic, I don’t think the distinction is salient – مكان (makaan) refers to both space and place, and it comes from the root for being and entities. The related word كون refers to the universe, all of God’s creation, the geography of which might be less human and more divine than I’m used to. Overall, I’m left thinking that we all have peculiar ideas of locality.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflections"/><category term="language"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[The space/place dichotomy is inverted by looking at it from East or West.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">What comes after irony?</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/What-comes-after-irony/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What comes after irony?"/><published>2025-01-18T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-18T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/What%20comes%20after%20irony</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/What-comes-after-irony/"><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/rorty/">Richard Rorty</a> was the most admirably plain-speaking of American philosophers. Since reading <em>Contingency, Irony, and Solidarity</em> (1987) as an undergraduate, I’ve thought of myself as a Rortian like Rorty thought of himself as a Deweyan. In short, Rorty’s ironist is someone who “has radical and continuing doubts about their <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vocabulary#Final_vocabulary" title="Vocabulary">final vocabulary</a>” and “does not think their vocabulary is closer to reality than others.” Personally, it made sense for me to give up questions I viewed as unproductive – especially after reading <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/John_Rawls#Philosophical_thought">John Rawls</a>, whose premises begin where I don’t want to end up (i.e., as an unencumbered self, devoid of peculiar values). Rorty the ironist gave me a philosophical vocabulary for responding with a “yes, I see your point, but anyway, I am what I am and like what people like me do, and so it seems for those other people too.”</p> <p>It took me years at Stanford to realize myself and how fortunate I am to begin my career where Rorty ended his. So, over the past couple weeks, I ducked into the archive to go through his papers. What I read deepened my appreciation for the man, who, with an iconoclastic gait, walked his own path and inspired me to walk mine.</p> <p>We have our differences. Rorty struggled to <a href="https://cdclv.unlv.edu/pragmatism/rorty_orchids.html">“hold reality and justice in a single vision,”</a> in my view because he never developed a good alternative to liberal elites’ dissociation. He acknowledged that “lucky Christians for whom the love of God and of other human beings are inseparable, or revolutionaries” might not feel the reality/justice split. But Rorty’s milieu was at once too continental and too pragmatic for him to be unironically hopeful.</p> <p>That never stopped him from speaking as though we could achieve our imagined possibilities. Rorty became a popular philosopher by saying that Americans, like philosophers, often ask the wrong questions. That made space for hope, for people to ask their own rather than respond to suppositions. As for himself, Rorty wrote in a memo re: <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_Posner">Richard Posner’s</a> pragmatism:</p> <ul> Disassociating the higher, in the sense of what breaks with the way things merely happen to be, from the blindingly clear and from the universal – from the models of mathematics –<br/>What is there that might serve as a source of moral obligation? That is the only question that philosophers discuss that intrigues non-philosophers. </ul> <p>Rorty saw the dualisms in Western thought as attempts to answer the obligatory question: pure/impure, subject/object, sacred/profane, etc. He wrote that “The source of moral obligation must itself be perfectly pure.” It’s odd, but I think explainable, that Posner the legalist spurred this realization. Rorty concluded that “the imagination” or “poetry” is that pure source of obligation.</p> <p>Lastly, I quote from a two page memo Rorty wrote for himself on Laclau and Moffe’s <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hegemony_and_Socialist_Strategy"><em>Hegemony and Socialist Strategy</em></a> (1985). Judging by the folds and tatters on those two pages, Rorty brought the memo with him from the University of Virginia to Stanford. In it, he wrote:</p> <ul> The difference between us here is probably not worth arguing, because the difference between saying "we want everybody to have the same opportunities" and saying "we believe everybody has, by virtue of being human, the right to equal opportunities" is too thin to matter. I tend to regard the latter formulation as suspiciously metaphysical, but this may just be a symptom of over-sensitivity. <br/><br/> Laclau agrees with me that once the Philosophical is succeeded by the Political we will get narratives instead of philosophical systems, even of the relatively weak Habermasian "transcendental pragmatic" sort. Given this agreement, the only question that remains is whether "ironist" is the right word for somebody willing to affirm the groundlessness of the beliefs she dies for. Perhaps not. I may be trying to make this word do too much work; it seems to me right for Derrida in Paris, or even in jail in Prague, but I agree that it's probably not right for somebody at Auschwitz. </ul> <p>Is there any plain and honest word for an ironic urge to make something meaningful, or to make up something sacred? Eliade’s “hierophany” is honest but not plain. What about Milan Kundera’s “kitsch”? As ever, I come back to Japanese <em>aware</em> and aesthetics. The next things for me to read are <a href="https://www.degruyter.com/document/doi/10.1515/9780791484838-008/html">David L. Hall’s “Rorty, Whitehead, and the Return of the Exiled Poets”</a> (2012) and <a href="https://whiteheadresearch.org/research/contemporary-whitehead-studies/book-list/tragic-beauty/">Steve Odin’s <em>Tragic Beauty in Whitehead and Japanese Aesthetics</em></a> (2016).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflections"/><category term="philosophy"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Rorty's iconoclastic "ironist" runs into trouble when they want to create something people can act on.]]></summary></entry></feed>