<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" xml:lang="en"><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.3.4">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml"/><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" hreflang="en"/><updated>2025-01-15T06:50:02+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Ballföðr’s Hall (aka JBall’s Site)</title><subtitle>Jon Ball&apos;s personal site. </subtitle><entry><title type="html">Reflections on Tarkovsky’s Stalker</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Reflections-on-Tarkovsky's-Stalker/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reflections on Tarkovsky’s Stalker"/><published>2025-01-13T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-13T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Reflections%20on%20Tarkovsky&apos;s%20Stalker</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Reflections-on-Tarkovsky&apos;s-Stalker/"><![CDATA[<p><em>(Please watch the movie yourself before reading about my opinions, or anyone else’s for that matter. If you need an apéritif, take Tarkovsky’s own words: “I am often asked what does this Zone stand for. There is only one possible answer: the Zone doesn’t exist. Stalker himself invented the Zone. He created it, so that he would be able to bring there some very unhappy persons and impose on them the idea of hope.”)</em> <br/><br/><br/></p> <p>The Zone is nothing other than nature – ours and in itself. That’s my take on <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stalker_(1979_film)"><em>Stalker</em>, a wonderfully abstract 1979 film</a> that enables multiple interpretations. Each scene is madly precise, and <a href="https://www.criterion.com/current/posts/4739-stalker-meaning-and-making">filmmaking lore</a> makes Andrei Tarkovsky’s achievement seem even greater (and more ruthless). The titular stalker is a man who can lead others to the brink of self-reflection but does not allow himself. In his stubborn refusal, together with the writer and professor, to enter the Room – the domain of deepest desire – we see the religiosity Tarkovsky wanted to convey. But if not for the unseen hand of soviet correction,[^1] Tarkovsky might have dwelled too much on <em>The Idiot</em> and <em>The Death of Ivan Ilyich</em> and made something else entirely. That would have been a shame, because what we have instead is as impersonal an artistic depiction of humanity as I have ever seen.[^2]</p> <p>I usually dislike pat takes, but Geoff Dyer’s description of <a href="https://youtu.be/Q3hBLv-HLEc?feature=shared&amp;t=38">the opening credits scene</a> is pat in the word’s positive sense (although I prefer <a href="https://www.slantmagazine.com/film/stalker/">Nick Schager’s take</a> overall):</p> <ul> An empty bar, possibly not even open, with a single table, no bigger than a small round table, but higher, the sort you then lean against – there are no stools – while you stand and drink. If floorboards could speak these look like they could tell a tale or two, though the tales would turn out to be one and the same, ending with the same old lament (after a few drinks people think they can walk all over me) not just in terms of what happens here, but in bars the world over. We are, in other words, already in a realm of universal truth.<br/>(Zona: A Book About a Film About a Journey to a Room, 2012) </ul> <p>Trying to make sense of <em>Stalker</em> is like trying to compose a subjective, universal theory of human nature. The actors – <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alexander_Kaidanovsky">Kaidanovsky</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anatoly_Solonitsyn">Solonitsyn</a>, <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Nikolai_Grinko">Grinko</a>, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Alisa_Freindlich">Freindlich</a> – projected their own, as did the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arkady_and_Boris_Strugatsky">brothers Strugatsky</a>, who wrote the source material, and of course, so did <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Andrei_Tarkovsky">Tarkovsky</a>. Some theories are truthier than others, however, and the interpretation I propose is inescapable.</p> <p>One view is that the Zone represents the stalker’s self-aware illusions, as Tarkovsky said. Another view, the one I hold, is that the Zone is nature incarnate. The two views are inseparable. A distinction could be drawn between one man’s nature and human nature, but it would just as soon disappear. Similarly, we could live in a natural world devoid of anything holy, but we would not live for long.</p> <p>Why, except for the opportunity to stage a <a href="https://youtu.be/Q3hBLv-HLEc?feature=shared&amp;t=1833">daring escape from the USSR</a>, would the screenwriters and director depict the trio of stalker, writer, and professor being shot at while entering the Zone? Allegorical quashing of the personal is a would-be dissident’s thing, surely. In that case, monitoring and informing on one another are what kill. But the Zone is devoid of intelligence operatives. And while the writer and professor betray their promises to the stalker, to respect him, they do not betray him to the guards. The barbed wire around the Zone is just another barricade erected to prevent natural reactions to suffering at the hands of others, and it might as well be in America.</p> <p>The <a href="https://youtu.be/Q3hBLv-HLEc?feature=shared&amp;t=5156">film’s most allegorical scene</a> flows up a shallow river, amid which the stalker sleeps on an ait, before coming to his outstretched, Michelangelesque hand. This particular scene was shot in sepia tones – the visual code used in the film to signify that the stalker is back in modern existence, although he is simultaneously dreaming inside the Zone. Trawling up the river, we see all kinds of creations: a submerged Orthodox icon, for example, as well as machines and syringes. But the image that caught my eye first was a bowl submerged inside the river with fish inside it, shown as soon as the monologue fades. Is the fishbowl a sanctuary or a prison? To my mind, that is the crux.</p> <p>Tarkovsky had this to say in <em>Sculpting in Time</em> (1987):</p> <ul> This, too, is what Stalker is about: the hero goes through moments of despair when his faith is shaken; but every time he comes to a renewed sense of his vocation to serve people who have lost their hopes and illusions. </ul> <p>The way he moves in the Zone clarifies things: the stalker leads from behind. The others try going their separate paths, but they reunite. No movement is unilinear, and only natural man[^3] can determine where they are going – by sortilege, it seems to the modern intelligentsia. Finally, the three of them just <a href="https://youtu.be/Q3hBLv-HLEc?feature=shared&amp;t=8395">sit together</a> at the Room’s entrance, the professor fiddling with a gadget and testing the water by throwing stones, the writer beside the hero pensively gazing at their reflection, and the stalker perhaps content for their company. He rues their nihilism in the end, but still, they came to him for inspiration (and as his voluminous book collection later shows, he to them).</p> <p>But wait, you might ask, how could the Zone be about nature (ours and Earth’s) when <a href="https://youtu.be/Q3hBLv-HLEc?feature=shared&amp;t=2738">it was said to have been created by a meteorite, or not a meteorite exactly</a>? Speculation on the matter has featured atomic bombs and Chernobyl disasters, in addition to the alien visitation described in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Roadside_Picnic">the Strugatskys’ novel</a>. In any event, we often give life to that which takes it away. We also forbid some mortal creations, because we know it is in our nature to abuse them. The more prudent question, in my opinion, is how could authorities forbid certain expressions of our nature, and when should we accept them?</p> <p>Let Tarkovsky’s words from <em>Sculpting in Time</em> conclude things:</p> <ul> People have often asked me what The Zone is, and what it symbolizes… The Zone doesn’t symbolise anything, any more than anything else does in my films: the zone is a zone, it’s life. </ul> <p>In exile, facing his own mortality, he wrote:</p> <ul> In the end, everything can be reduced to the one simple element which is all a person can count upon in his existence: the capacity to love. </ul> <p>That too is only natural. <br/><br/> <br/> [1] Do not discount fate, either: A literal earthquake prevented filming in Tajikistan and necessitated a move to Estonia, while a corrupted film reel supposedly forced the director to re-film the present version from scratch.</p> <p>[2] In case you do not find the film sufficiently impersonal, read into the lore: Tarkovsky may have killed himself, his wife Larisa, and the writer (actor Anatoly Solonitsyn) by filming three separate takes, all the while surrounded by chemicals from hydroelectric and manufacturing plants near Tallinn. They each died in middle age of lung cancer.</p> <p>[3] Forgive me for pointing out that the writer says he imagined the stalker like “Leather Stocking, or Chingachgook, or Big Snake” – referring to James Fenimore Cooper’s Mohican character inventions. Dante’s Virgil is nowhere in sight.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reviews"/><category term="cinema"/><category term="nature"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Why not face our nature? This 1979 masterpiece was shaped by the director's struggle with soviet censorship, from mere science fiction or religious allegory into something truly universal.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">From East to West, the Stars</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/From-East-to-West,-the-Stars/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="From East to West, the Stars"/><published>2025-01-11T23:33:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-11T23:33:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/From%20East%20to%20West,%20the%20Stars</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/From-East-to-West,-the-Stars/"><![CDATA[<p>Outside West College, the first hall built at my alma mater – then located in West Township, MA – stands Hopkins Memorial Gate. It’s taboo to go through before graduating, but I often did anyway because it was a pain to go around without walking over icy grass or perpendicular sidewalks. Maybe that’s why I barely remember passing through it during Commencement, in line with tradition. Oops. The gate features an aphoristic poem that now serves as college motto:</p> <div style="display: flex; justify-content: space-between;"> <div class="col-sm-6"> Climb High<br/> Climb Far<br/> Your Goal<br/> The Sky<br/> Your Aim<br/> The Star </div> <div class="col-sm-6"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2025-01-11-Climb-far-grid3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2025-01-11-Climb-far-grid3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2025-01-11-Climb-far-grid3-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-01-11-Climb-far-grid3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div> <p>Its enthusiasm for youth complements the old motto, <em>E liberalitate E. Williams, armigeri</em>.</p> <p>Seven to ten years later, while studying near Palo Alto, CA at “the Cornell of the West,” I took a weekend trip down to Carmel-by-the-Sea. Bringing along a girlfriend from NYC, I really wanted to see <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eyvind_Earle">Eyvind Earle’s</a> paintings at <a href="https://gallery21.com/">gallery21</a>. Eyvind (eye-vind) Earle led a full career but is best known for illustrating the expressionistic backgrounds in Disney’s <em>Sleeping Beauty</em> (1959). Earle was the central coast’s best appreciator (apart from Robinson Jeffers[^1]), and a fellow NY transplant who repeatedly painted views of the Santa Lucia range rolling down to meet the Pacific. The gallery owner told me that Earle worked like a mystic, hanging all his WIPs around the studio and working on them simultaneously, one touch at a time. ADHD, I first thought, but cohesiveness I now recognize. A poem was displayed in the gallery’s front window:</p> <ul> Starting from nothing <br/> to where we are,<br/> is farther than the farthest star.<br/><br/> And farther than the farthest star,<br/> is where we are going from where we are.<br/><br/> – Eyvind Earle, 1979 </ul> <p>Youthful hubris gives way to aged wisdom, and the world keeps turning. Earle’s poem was beside this painting:</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2025-01-11-CRASHING-WAVE-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2025-01-11-CRASHING-WAVE-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2025-01-11-CRASHING-WAVE-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-01-11-CRASHING-WAVE.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>[1] For coming back to: Jeffers’s “Meditation on Saviors,” in <em>Cawdor and Other Poems</em> (1928).</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reflections"/><category term="poetry"/><category term="art"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Two poems I encountered toward the beginning and end of my formal education make for a humbling arc.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Acts of Fact and Fetish</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Acts-of-Fact-and-Fetish/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Acts of Fact and Fetish"/><published>2025-01-10T21:30:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-10T21:30:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Acts%20of%20Fact%20and%20Fetish</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Acts-of-Fact-and-Fetish/"><![CDATA[<p>Smash the fetish and we are suddenly in the process of gathering it (or something else like it) back together. This is the thrust of Bruno Latour’s 1996 essay, translated as “On the Cult of the Factish Gods” (2010).[^1] Latour’s moral was that we should stop believing in belief, because truth and facts are always made up through action and dialogue, and if we sanctify what we make instead of the process of making, then we lose our power. A few years later (1998), Richard Rorty and Bjørn Ramberg, following Donald Davidson’s lead, concluded that accounts of truth are automatically accounts of agency. Rorty called this the “inescapability of the normative.”[^2] When similar ideas emerge at once in different places, a significant event has occurred. The next step, I think, is theorizing internormativity, or a multilingual meta-ethics.</p> <p>But for now, I am back at Latour’s essay, which is tricky and enlightening. I got lost in its thicket of wordplays and references, so I intend this post as a guide for returning to. Here is a summary of the main point about fetishes:</p> <ul> ... even among the Moderns, the fetish, far from being drained of its efficacy, always seems to act in such a way as to shift, muddle, invert, and perturb the origins of belief, as well as the very certainty that mastery is possible. The fetish immediately regains the power that people seek to deny it.[^3] </ul> <p>Latour’s opening figures[^4] depict what all this is generally about:</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig2-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig2-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig2-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig2.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig3-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig3-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig3-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig3.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig4-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig4-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig4-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig4.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>These show the process of debunking and its obverse (rebunking?), although “power” is missing, which explains the asymmetry behind Latour’s symmetrical design. The subtext is moral – should we Moderns be doing this to others? But the essay does not really get at the human heart of the matter, the <em>why</em>.</p> <p>Here is a passage that approximates <em>why</em>:</p> <ul> Why insist so strongly on an absolute distinction [between fact-objects and fairy-objects] that can never be applied? Because it is used precisely to redouble the advantages of practice with those of theory. The double repertoire of the Moderns cannot be discovered in their distinction between facts and fetishes, but in the *second*, more subtle distinction between the separation of facts from fetishes that they institute in theory, on the one hand, and the totally different passage from one to the other that they carry out in their practice, on the other. Belief then takes on a new meaning: it is what allows one to keep the practical form of life, in which one causes something to be fabricated, at a distance from the theoretical forms of life, in which one has to choose between facts and fetishes. This is how critical thinkers can go on purifying theory indefinitely, without having to face the possible consequences of their purification.[^5] </ul> <p>Latour got religious with the last sentence – why <em>do</em> we set apart theory from practice, despite everything? A unifying theory of our nature would show how real vagaries necessitate the distinction, but it remains elusive.</p> <p>So, Latour invented a new term instead:</p> <ul> Joining the two etymological sources [of fact and fetish], we shall use the label *factish* for the robust certainty that allows practice to pass into action without the practitioner ever believing in the difference between construction and reality, immanence and transcendence.(^23: One should add to this the artifact, in the laboratory sense of a parasite mistaken for a new being. Unlike facts, artifacts are surprising, because human actions can be discovered where they have not been expected. The word thus provides a transition between the surprise of facts and the surprise of fetishes. There is no more reason for giving up the word "fetish" than for giving up the word "fact," on the pretext that the Moderns believed in belief and wanted to disqualify the former term while retaining the latter. In practice, no one has ever believed in fetishes, and everyone has paid astute attention to facts. The two words thus remain intact. Since the phonemic difference between the French terms *fée* and *fait* ("fairy" and "fact") is not always audible, some might prefer *factiche* over *faitiche* in French. In the English "factish," the etymological link to "fairy" is unfortunately lost.) </ul> <p>I am uneasy with the claim that no one has ever believed in fetishes, although this is not to argue that no ever <em>practiced</em> a belief in fetishes. Following Mircea Eliade’s hierophany and Alexei Lidov’s hierotopy, and also de Certeau’s axiom that “space is practiced place,” it does seem that wherever fetishes feel most real, we find people practicing habits about them and thereby acting in line with (social?) facts. But this is relativistic in the extreme. My experiences as a guest among various communities have aligned with the idea that, regardless of place (but conditional on other things), we share a basic kind of moral reciprocity, or fundamental norms, or even the fear of god(‘s’) watchful eye. This could be called a fact of life, but our sacral behavior toward it puzzles me. Latour came around somewhere near this point, noting how we “continue doing what we have always done,” albeit with a practical justification and/or in secret:</p> <ul> The very notion of practice arises from the requirement that the Moderns impose. Since we cannot express ourselves in the either-or terms of critical thinking, we are obliged to continue doing what we have always done, but in secret.(^28: Amusingly enough, the pragmatism that could be taken for the philosophy of practice remains so intimidated by the authoritative position of its adversaries that it is forced to depict practice as modest, limited, utilitarian, humanist, and convenient, thereby occupying – unquestioningly – the place critical philosophy had prepared for it. Modesty is a philosophical virtue only if it decides for itself how it will keep from telling somebody what to do or from proposing foundations.) Practice is the clandestine wisdom of the passage that stubbornly maintains (but since it can no longer say so out loud, it is content merely to act accordingly, to murmur its message in hushed tones) that construction and reality are synonyms.[^6] </ul> <p>It will take time to sink in. Meanwhile, Latour prudently digressed on <em>Bhharathipura</em>, a 1973 novel by the Kannada-language writer U.R. Ananthamurthy. It tells the story of a Brahmin, Jagannantha, who blasphemes his ancestral religion by taking his family’s <em>shaligram</em>, a holy black stone (lit. an ammonite), from its sacred spot and trying to force members of a pariah caste to touch it. They do not. Jagannantha only succeeds in besmirching his own nest:</p> <ul> The priest, the aunt, and the pariahs already know what Jagannath discovers by his failure: it has nothing to do with belief, it is all about behavior. It is not about a fetish-stone, but about factishes, about those off-center beings that allow us to live, that is, to pass continually from construction to autonomy without ever believing in either. Thanks to factishes, construction and truth remain synonymous. Once broken, they become antonyms. We can no longer pass. We can no longer create. We can no longer live. Then we have to set up factishes all over again.[^7] </ul> <p>Here, the wellspring of facts and fairies ran dry, so Latour code-switched into the “language of philosophers” and plumbed it again:</p> <ul> "[The] stubborn refusal to choose [between immanence and transcendence]... always shows up, we now understand, as a simple practice, as something that can never be spoken or theorized, even if the 'actors-themselves' keep on saying it and describing it in luxurious detail.(^32: ... [T]his amounts to generalizing an ethnomethodological approach by extending it into metaphysics by way of semiotics, the only *organon* we have at our disposal that can fearlessly maintain the diversity of modes of existence – at the price, to be sure, of putting them into language and text, a restriction that we have nonetheless sought to overcome by extending the overly-restrictive definition of semiotics to things themselves. And so once again we come across the entities that had interested us from the start – under the vague heading of "actor-network" – and that are at once real, social, and discursive.)[^8] </ul> <p><em>Voilà</em>. But since we grasp things better when they have concise names like “actor-network theory,” I prefer Rorty’s parsimonious phrasing: Any account of truth is automatically an account of agency. This leaves open the question of how to make up an actual research method that models people and their dialogic processes of truth making, their crafts for fabricating fetishes, their science in action, etc.</p> <p>Latour preferred ethnography, and his footnotes also say: go read Tobie Nathan and Isabelle Stengers. He could not resist another coinage, however, and in his pamphlet’s last trick, he made up the word “transfears” after observing a patient’s diagnosis at a psychiatric clinic. Evidently tiring of factishes, Latour instead began using “divinities” to describe how an objective temperament – a mental syndrome, or perhaps, an orisha – comes to be seated on one’s head. Religious initiation and psychiatric diagnosis require the conferral / transferal of a supposedly new status, hence why he reached for a new word:</p> <ul> Let us venture one more term to define these divinities at last. I propose to call them "fears," borrowing Tobie Nathan's lovely explanation for this word, which has the advantage of presuming neither essence nor person.(^62: Nathan, *L'influence qui guérit*. Nathan contrasts "anguish" and "fright." Anguish is supposed to have no outside cause and comes entirely from the subject's own projection; fright, on the contrary is clearly the realization that there is something outside that has caused you to be frightened.)[^9] </ul> <p>Much earlier, around 1665, François de La Rochefoucauld expressed fear’s incitement of action in <em>Maximes</em>, no. 38:</p> <ul> Nous promettons selon nos espérances, et nous tenons nos craintes. / Promises are made according to our hopes, and kept according to our fears.[^10] </ul> <p><strong>Perhaps ethnographies of fear phenomena can describe both facts and fetishes, or why we make and worship them, better than philosophies – something I will continue to ponder.</strong> But for now, I am quite finished with Latour’s essay and will leave further discussion of his iconoclasm for another time.</p> <p>Finally, here are some closing quotes and figures to bookend the discussion:</p> <ul> No one, in practice, has ever displayed naive belief in any being whatsoever.(^43: From one year to the next, each of the canonical examples finds itself overturned by modern historiography, as in the admirable case studied by Jeffrey Burton Russell in *Inventing the Flat Earth: Columbus and Modern Historians* (1991). How those monks have been mocked for being naive enough to believe in a flat earth in the literal sense. The author proves, with brio, that this particular belief in naive belief dates back to the nineteenth century, when there was actually nothing naive about it, since it shared in the beautiful Enlightenment scenography that was emerging from the dark ages.) If there is such a thing as belief at all, it is the most complex, sophisticated, critical, subtle, reflective activity there is.(^44: Catherine Darbo-Peschanski's *Le discours du particulier: Essai sur l'enquête hérodotéene* (1987). This has been a decisive work for me: it can serve as an overall method for bringing together the diversity of positions that has been crushed by the notion of belief. For more recent examples, see Émilie Gomart, "Methodone: Six Effects in Search of a Substance," *Social Studies of Science 32, no.1 (2002): 93-135.) But this subtlety can never unfold if one first attempts to break it down into cause-objects, source-subjects, and representations. To take away the ontology of belief, on the pretext that it occurs inside the subject, is to misunderstand objects and human actors alike. It is to miss the wisdom of the factishes.[^11] </ul> <p>Denouement (all following correspond to a single footnote below)[^12]:</p> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig8-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig8-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig8-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig8.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Quote:</p> <ul> Instead of a causal chain transmitting a force that actualizes a potential, realizes a possibility, you will never obtain more than a series of slight surpassings. Events: here is another name for the factishes and the worship they deserve. </ul> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig9-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig9-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig9-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-01-10-fig9.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> <p>Quote:</p> <ul> Really? Is an engineer master of his machine? Was Pasteur master of his lactic acid? Is a programmer master of his program, a creator, of his creation, an author, of his text? No one who has ever truly acted could utter such impieties. It is because God is a creature and because our creations possess, in relationship to ourselves, as much autonomy as we possess in relationship to God, that we can continue to use the words "construction" and "creation" without lying.(^83: Discoveries in theology are rare; but Whitehead's discovery of the creature god certainly counts as one. Indeed, for Whitehead it was less a matter of discovering than of understanding, through a different language, what everybody had already understood in a different way: Whitehead's god is *incarnate*. "All actual entities share with God this characteristic of self-causation. For this reason every actual entity also shares with God the characteristic of transcending all other actual entities, including God" (*Process and Reality: An Essay in Cosomology*. New York: Free Press, 1978, 222). To believe that God will now submerge himself among his creatures is to keep on repeating the same mistake. Creatures are not immanent. Mediations, events, passages, and *factishes* can be used neither for drowning, nor for dissolving, but only for producing. They come to pass. They differ.) </ul> <p>Finally:</p> <ul> In the common world of comparative anthropology, lights cross paths. Differences are not there to be respected, neglected, or subsumed, but, as Whitehead said, to act as "lures for feelings, food for thought." </ul> <p>As priests say, <em>amen</em>, and neurochemists say <em>amine</em>.</p> <div style="page-break-after: always;"></div> <p>[1] Bruno Latour and Catherine Porter, <em>On the Modern Cult of the Factish Gods</em> (Duke University Press, 2010).</p> <p>[2] Richard Rorty, 29 December 1998, “Response to Bjorn Ramberg,” Richard Rorty papers, M2558 Box 2, Folder 2, Special Collections and Archives, Green Library, Stanford University, 1.</p> <p>[3] Latour and Porter, “Factish Gods,” 11.</p> <p>[4] <em>Ibid.,</em> 12-15.</p> <p>[5] <em>Ibid.,</em> 20-21.</p> <p>[6] <em>Ibid.,</em> 24.</p> <p>[7] <em>Ibid.,</em> 28.</p> <p>[8] <em>Ibid.</em></p> <p>[9] <em>Ibid.,</em> 52.</p> <p>[10] The Duc de La Rochefoucauld, <em>Reflections, or Moral Opinions &amp; Maxims: a bilingual edition</em>, trans. Jack Mitchell (CreateSpace Independent, 2017), 25.</p> <p>[11] Latour and Porter, “Factish Gods,” 42.</p> <p>[12] <em>Ibid.,</em> 63-66.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reviews"/><category term="language"/><category term="religion"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[After reading Latour's "Cult of the Factish Gods," I think the truth is that we believe what we fear.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why the fetish?</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Why-the-fetish/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why the fetish?"/><published>2025-01-09T07:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-09T07:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Why%20the%20fetish</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Why-the-fetish/"><![CDATA[<p>Chapter 1 of Bruno Latour’s <a href="https://www.dukeupress.edu/On-the-Modern-Cult-of-the-Factish-Gods"><em>On the Modern Cult of the Factish Gods</em> (2010)</a> uses etymology, homonymy, and general artifice to make the claim that facts are modern fetishes. Thus, while we may claim to be secular and scientific in public, we have never been areligious. This continues Latour’s theme of symmetry, earlier developed in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/We_Have_Never_Been_Modern"><em>We Have Never Been Modern</em> (1993)</a>. I approve of the cleverness. Mating ideas to the historical peculiarities of the words we use to express them is something that Heidegger did splendidly in his lecture on <a href="https://monoskop.org/images/1/1d/Heidegger_Martin_1950_2000_Das_Ding.pdf"><em>Das Ding</em> (“The Thing”)</a>, and Latour carried the torch well.[^1] Tellingly, however, the uglier neologism “iconoclash” was instead ported to <a href="https://zkm.de/de/ausstellung/2002/05/iconoclash">Germany for a 2002 art installation</a>, the written accompaniment to which makes up chapter 2 of the book. Then chapter 3 is a closing sermon on scientism. Overall, I agree with the claim that our practices and taboos about science are weirdly religious. But the English fête prepared for Latour by Duke Press was unwarranted.</p> <p>The pamphlet adapted into chapter 1, <a href="https://fr.wikipedia.org/wiki/Petite_r%C3%A9flexion_sur_le_culte_moderne_des_dieux_faitiches"><em>Petite réflexion sur le culte moderne des dieux faitiches</em> (1996)</a>, pretends to show a little more humility than the translated version. Reading the English is daunting, not only for its density, but for its pretentious style and numerous footnotes. That said, <a href="https://dspace.mit.edu/bitstream/handle/1721.1/116668/669026.pdf?sequence=1">as Rosalind Williams emphasized in her review</a>, the footnotes are illuminating. (Some generous soul also underlined the most interesting passages in the copy of the book I borrowed from Stanford’s library, so I take back what I wrote about the fête.) Tomorrow I will post a secondhand homily and a selection of quotes.</p> <div style="page-break-after: always;"></div> <div style="page-break-after: always;"></div> <p>[1] Rorty reminded us that this is Europa’s torch: “Analytical philosophers think in terms of questions without history, whereas continental philosophers think in terms of names with history.”</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reviews"/><category term="language"/><category term="religion"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Latour's «faitiche» ("factish") is normanesque trickery, and his "iconoclash" is an artsy rehash of Sombart's creative destruction.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Through with Euphemism</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Through-with-Euphemism/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Through with Euphemism"/><published>2025-01-08T05:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-08T05:00:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Through%20with%20Euphemism</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/Through-with-Euphemism/"><![CDATA[<p><em>Nineteen Eighty-Four</em> has its roots in George Orwell’s 1945 essay <a href="https://www.orwellfoundation.com/the-orwell-foundation/orwell/essays-and-other-works/politics-and-the-english-language/">“Politics and the English Language.”</a> Orwell published the piece in <em>Horizon</em>, a literary journal styled as a successor to T.S. Eliot’s <em>The Criterion</em>, and whatever the intervening criticism of Orwell’s work or this essay in particular, I think it reads brilliantly in 2025. This post offers a selection of quotations and my notes. But before digging in, I want to get out my critiques.</p> <p>First, Orwell wrote as if modern English is especially inane. He disregarded the fact that most writers and speakers throughout history have recited, at least on occasion, nonsense in service of politics. Second, context is missing from Orwell’s account. For example, I assume that liberal warfare harms language as does dictatorship, and that mass media of the kinds introduced during Orwell’s lifetime do not help. Third, the essay’s “catalogue of swindles and perversions” and its formulaic tips for better writing distract readers from the main idea, that genuine thought is being replaced by doubletalk, euphemizing, and willful distortion.[^1]</p> <p>Form affects content, and vice versa, so I agree with the claim that politics and language can be mutually degrading. The notion that patriotism forbids sincere communication is as apparent after 9/11 as it was after WWII. Hence we have a war on terror, which <em>implies</em> the murder of muslims and their families. But enough of that.</p> <p>Here are some of my favorite bits from Orwell’s influential essay.</p> <p>His argument and advice required less than a paragraph:</p> <ul> A scrupulous writer, in every sentence that he writes, will ask himself at least four questions, thus: What am I trying to say? What words will express it? What image or idiom will make it clearer? Is this image fresh enough to have an effect? And he will probably ask himself two more: Could I put it more shortly? Have I said anything that is avoidably ugly? But you are not obliged to go to all this trouble. You can shirk it by simply throwing your mind open and letting the ready-made phrases come crowding in. They will construct your sentences for you – even think your thoughts for you, to a certain extent – and at need they will perform the important service of partially concealing your meaning even from yourself. It is at this point that the special connection between politics and the debasement of language becomes clear. </ul> <p>I find it ironic whenever someone advocates English becoming less of a bastard tongue, but I appreciate the call to action:</p> <ul> There is a long list of fly-blown metaphors which could similarly be got rid of if enough people would interest themselves in the job; and it should also be possible to laugh the *not un-* formation out of existence, to reduce the amount of Latin and Greek in the average sentence, to drive out foreign phrases and strayed scientific words, and, in general, to make pretentiousness unfashionable. </ul> <p>Then, with resolute irony, the essay continues:</p> <ul> [The defence of the English language] has nothing to do with archaism, with the salvaging of obsolete words and turns of speech, or with the setting up of a ‘standard English’ which must never be departed from. On the contrary, it is especially concerned with the scrapping of every word or idiom which has outworn its usefulness. It has nothing to do with correct grammar and syntax, which are of no importance so long as one makes one’s meaning clear or with the avoidance of Americanisms, or with having what is called a ‘good prose style’. On the other hand it is not concerned with fake simplicity and the attempt to make written English colloquial. Nor does it even imply in every case preferring the Saxon word to the Latin one, though it does imply using the fewest and shortest words that will cover one’s meaning. What is above all needed is to let the meaning choose the word, and not the other way about. </ul> <p>It ends with a weaker exhortation, but one I still abide:</p> <ul> Political language – and with variations this is true of all political parties, from Conservatives to Anarchists – is designed to make lies sound truthful and murder respectable, and to give an appearance of solidity to pure wind. One cannot change this all in a moment, but one can at least change one’s own habits, and from time to time one can even, if one jeers loudly enough, send some worn-out and useless phrase... into the dustbin where it belongs. </ul> <p>I omitted Orwell’s selection of worn-out phrases from the quotation above, as they are now dead. Instead, I propose binning current Orwellian phrases like <em>stand with</em>, <em>trumpism</em>, <em>content creator</em>, <em>privacy policy</em>, and <em>making progress</em>.</p> <p>Lastly, since a picture is worth a thousand words (pardon the trite phrase), I leave behind a scan of Ostrom and Haltom’s (2018) propaganda chart, which compares Orwell’s approach in “Politics and the English Language” (1945) with Jacques Ellul’s in <em>Propagandes</em> (1962)[^2].</p> <p>[1] See Irony Two – Gripes and Gibes, in Hans Ostrom and William Haltom, <em>Orwell’s “Politics and the English Language” in the Age of Pseudocracy</em> (Routledge, 2018), 3.</p> <p>[2] <em>Ibid.,</em> 46.</p> <div class="row mt-3"> <div class="col-sm mt-3 mt-md-0"> <figure> <picture> <source class="responsive-img-srcset" srcset="/assets/img/2025-01-07-chart-480.webp 480w,/assets/img/2025-01-07-chart-800.webp 800w,/assets/img/2025-01-07-chart-1400.webp 1400w," type="image/webp" sizes="95vw"/> <img src="/assets/img/2025-01-07-chart.jpg" class="img-fluid rounded z-depth-1" width="100%" height="auto" data-zoomable="" loading="eager" onerror="this.onerror=null; $('.responsive-img-srcset').remove();"/> </picture> </figure> </div> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="reviews"/><category term="language"/><category term="politics"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[George Orwell criticized pseudocratic language. We should too.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Philological Specificity of Things (For Gaza)</title><link href="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/The-Philological-Specificity-of-Things-(For-Gaza)/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Philological Specificity of Things (For Gaza)"/><published>2025-01-07T00:20:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-01-07T00:20:00+00:00</updated><id>https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/The%20Philological%20Specificity%20of%20Things%20(For%20Gaza)</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://jballhalla.github.io/blog/2025/The-Philological-Specificity-of-Things-(For-Gaza)/"><![CDATA[<p>«لا وَطَنٌ ولا منفى هِيَ الكلماتُ»</p> <p>“Neither a homeland nor exile is the word.”</p> <p>– Mahmoud Darwish, “To Describe Almond Blossoms”<sup id="fnref:1"><a href="#fn:1" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">1</a></sup></p> <p>In his meta-commentary on critique, Bruno Latour dispensed with Heidegger’s treatment of the thing (<em>Das Ding</em>), as distinct from an object (<em>Gegenstand</em>).<sup id="fnref:2"><a href="#fn:2" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">2</a></sup> The crux of the distinction is not just a matter of construction, but of timing – for a thing to be, first a human being(s) must conceive of it, presumably for some social purpose, and then it can be a thing as well as an object. However, timing is an insufficient mechanism for the emergence of things, let alone objects, and nostalgia clouds the distinction. Latour took gathering to be the real mechanism at play. As people gather around technologies, for example, they become more of a thing. This necessitates a shift about matters of fact and matters of concern, which really are the same. Now, as an ontic intervention, Latour’s essay has fallen flat. But in its spirit, I want to argue that, while all things share roots, specific languages mediate specific things – with a whole lot of code switching in-between. Should we remain too permissive of this code switching (and really, doubletalk), then objects will finally take precedence, at least over the lives of Palestinians.</p> <p>The coincidence of matters of fact and concern is worth considering in most areas of our lives, not least in our relationship to technology. But I struggle to think up a method of coincidence, except to show how things are overdetermined – demonstrating polysemy in other words, or multiple realization. I would mainly use human language to do so. For example: Similarity is a property of people who share things in common, and it is also a property of points and vectors close by in a space. Machine learning systems are programmed to make content recommendations based on both kinds of similarity, with implications for both kinds of similarity. Maybe language is not required to put this point across. Latour borrowed Alfred North Whitehead’s example of a sunset being both physical and aesthetic,<sup id="fnref:3"><a href="#fn:3" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">3</a></sup> so I suppose I could sit silently and appreciate the beauty while blocking the rays with a pair of sunglasses. But I admire language in its many forms, and I am sure that we can do nothing without it, and we therefore must care for it.</p> <p>Philological specificity refers to the thingness of different languages. It evokes the worst of Heidegger’s takes, but let me try to make it a thing, a gathering of love for the word and all it can mediate instead. I am, after all, following Latour’s suggestion to go “[n]ot westward, but so to speak, eastward.”<sup id="fnref:4"><a href="#fn:4" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">4</a></sup> The fact is that various human languages share expressions for gathering up objects and things, as well as concepts for bringing together nature and humanity, not to mention the divine. These are by nature idiomatic. Spanish has an appropriate turn of phrase: “Cada cosa es para lo que es.” Heidegger’s <em>Das Ding</em><sup id="fnref:5"><a href="#fn:5" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">5</a></sup> is therefore limited by its specific etymology. To remedy this, the kinds of things I will now consider, in Arabic and Hebrew, are arguably more theological. Their metaphysics perspicuously contrast with Heideggerian objects and things, although Latour devoted a great deal to softening those edges, and code switching does more still.</p> <p>To begin: <em>Inshallah</em> (إن شاء الله) is perhaps the most ubiquitous Arabic phrase, eliding three words together. It means: “If God wills (it into being).” Some secular approximations are “Hope so!” and “We’ll see.” The expression’s middle word, <em>shaa’a</em> (شاء), is a verb people can use to want or to wish, and it shares a three-letter root (ش ي ء ) with one of the Arabic words meaning “thing” (شيء ). Apart from grammar, this word for thing also means object. Thus, both things and objects can be about brought about through divine emanation. Even the definite article in Arabic, <em>al</em> (ال), is definite by virtue of its attachment to Allah’s Goodly Names (أسماء الله الحسنى) – The Most Merciful, for example. So, at least one translation into Arabic of the title of Heidegger’s essay “The Thing” would be doubly divinely inflected.</p> <p>The point is that things in Arabic relate to monotheism in a way that complicates Heidegger’s metaphysics. With the word of God comes His metaphysics, and some Arabic conventions reinforce this. What does that mean for science? Well, if nature, humans, and the divine are gathered from the first word, then secularism of the kind abided by Latour indicates a poverty of conception. In his 11th century treatise <em>tahaafut al-filaasifa</em> (<em>The Incoherence of the Philosophers</em>), al-Ghazali took issue with fellow Muslim intellectuals who worked in Arabic, like Ibn Sina (Avicenna) and al-Farabi, because they were content to have God as a first cause and apply reason to everything that comes after. But al-Ghazali saw that God is always imminent, and he made an epistemic claim that faith in the divine was required for understanding and explanation. Never mind that he and many of his contemporaries were Persian and used other words for things too.</p> <p> al-Ghazali’s positions were extreme, and an Andalusian scholar named Ibn Rushd (b. 1126) critiqued them on Aristotelian grounds in a cleverly constructed reply, <em>tahaafut al-tahaafut</em> (<em>The Incoherence of Incoherence</em>). This act would be well received by European and Jewish scholars. For example, Ibn Rushd rejected al-Ghazali’s occasionalism – the idea that everything we do is in effect done by God.<sup id="fnref:6"><a href="#fn:6" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">6</a></sup> Ibn Rushd, whose Latinized name is Averroes, used the Arabic word to connote things as they are (pure being):</p> <p>“[I]t is self-evident that things have essences and attributes that determine the special functions of each thing and through which the essences and names of things are differentiated. If a thing did not have its specific nature, it would not have a special name nor a definition, and all things would be one[.]”<sup id="fnref:7"><a href="#fn:7" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">7</a></sup></p> <p>Here, Arabic things, objects, and the divine coincide with Aristotelian context. By code switching into a new set of connotations and allowing for new gatherings, all in the context of a critique, Ibn Rushd presaged my argument. But as it is, I must be careful – all I am arguing is that thingness has its specificity, and that specificity inheres in language. Ever since Babel, people have been capable of learning one another’s languages and being in one another’s gatherings. There have always been physical limits to doing things together, and even as new technologies facilitate this, things will remain specific until the tower has been rebuilt stone for stone.</p> <p>On the matter of the Bible – in Jewish languages (and by no means exclusively), things are complex and subject to constant revision. Consider Moses ben Maimon (b. 1138), also called Maimonides and Rambam (רמב״ם), who was an influential Sephardic rabbi, philosopher, and contemporary of Ibn Rushd. His <em>Guide for the Perplexed</em> is a synthetic tour de force that plays at reconciling Aristotelian things as they are with multiple layers of philosophical, legal, and esoteric interpretation. Maimonides wrote the <em>Guide</em> in Egypt using Judeo-Arabic, a rendering of Classical Arabic into Hebrew script. This choice preserved the intertextuality and specificity of Hebrew, while also facilitating engagement with Arabic writings on Aristotle. Shalom Sadik (2022) states that subsequent interpretation of the <em>Guide</em> has come down to two major questions:</p> <p>1.        “Is it justified for the philosophical interpreter to assume that Maimonides’ philosophical opinion is actually radical, i.e., naturalist, despite Maimonides’ explicit rejection of naturalism in the Guide (for example II:29)? “</p> <p>2.        Does Maimonides think that humans can reach an unassailable knowledge of the secrets of religion and nature?”<sup id="fnref:8"><a href="#fn:8" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">8</a></sup></p> <p>I humbly suggest that these questions are related to Maimonides’s use of different words for things, such as the Arabic <em>‘amar</em> (أمر), also meaning issue, and the Hebrew <em>davar</em> (דָבָר), which connotes speech acts. He alternated between them in reference to al-Farabi’s and Avicenna’s transmission of Aristotle’s ideas, and the text of the Torah. Deeper kabbalistic meanings are things I will never know. Sadik argues that Hebrew translations of the <em>Guide</em> by Ibn Tibbon and al-Harizi went in different directions: al-Harizi inclined toward skepticism of the sufficiency of human reason, and Ibn Tibbon toward radicalism. Later translations have their roots.</p> <p>Dealing with multiple meanings is a challenge for those who would use multiple languages, and not just. The problem persists across translations of all kinds to this day. One way to resolve some of these issues, would be to identify a family resemblance. The philologists who influenced Heidegger did a great deal of this, hence the etymological specificity of “things,” like <em>dinge</em> and <em>alþingi</em> and all that. But resemblances among families of languages can mean less than their differences. Maimonides’s negative theology suggests a different kind of resolution for things, which is to state (sometimes repeatedly) what they are not. We know from a history of palimpsests and fragments that there are still more final ways to deal with polysemy: through words, in the way of things, as well as through the application of objects.</p> <p>I have so far neglected objects for things, mirroring Heidegger’s nostalgia for nature. It never went away. Still, objects make themselves known with force. Latour wrote at a time when “another extraordinary parallel event was occurring. This time a Thing—with a capital T—was assembled to try to coalesce, to gather in one decision, one object, one projection of force: a military strike against Iraq.”<sup id="fnref:9"><a href="#fn:9" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">9</a></sup> Before the WMDs were an object, I gather, they were a thing. Things can hardly be worse than they were during the Iraq War, responding to and responsible for terrible violence. But 20 years later, they are the same, and the object is just as terrible.</p> <p>It was said that architecture would never be the same after Ground Zero,<sup id="fnref:10"><a href="#fn:10" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">10</a></sup> and now, because of Gaza, neither will machine learning. “Lavender” is the English code name given to an AI model and an algorithm trained by data and computer scientists embedded in the IDF, with the stated purpose of anti-terrorism.<sup id="fnref:11"><a href="#fn:11" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">11</a></sup> To become an object, this system required the same kinds of assemblages detailed by Latour. In effect, it resembles prior objects, which may be automatic, but not to the same degree, and which are not probabilistic in the same way. The key difference is that deadly predictions are now made at the level of individuals based on personal information such as phone contacts, calls, texts, location, images, relations to lists of known targets, and other features that identify family resemblances. Sadly, false positives are a thing.</p> <p>Stalin supposedly said that while the death of one man is a tragedy, the death of a million is a statistic. The tragedies now number in the tens if not hundreds of thousands, and along with them their relatives’. I mentioned that machine learning systems are built to make recommendations according to mathematical proxies for similarity, corresponding for better or worse to real similarities, and with implications for both. What an awful relationship this is! The most inhumane part of the object is the ease with which it allows another human being to approve an act of oblivion, nonverbally and even alone, save now for a screen.</p> <p>What is thing theory’s response to these issues, to this state of affairs? “Lavender” might be ponderable by the masses for the present moment,<sup id="fnref:12"><a href="#fn:12" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">12</a></sup> but layers accumulate, and the matter is covered up by shatnez. Today, we are modern for using electricity to transmit things and power objects. But what has modernity done to Israel and Palestine? It will mean nothing if the movement is all ended. We therefore need something to pull us out from underneath the pile, and Latour was on the right track, in that Things must now seriously consider their enduring relation to the object. The consequence of thinking one-way like Heidegger is that no object is forbidden.</p> <p>Arabic in itself is perfectly capable of describing coincidence: «أحدث حدثا» – the event was spoken about into being. Suzanne Marchand has argued in as many words that “orientalism helped to <em>destroy</em> Western self-satisfaction,”<sup id="fnref:13"><a href="#fn:13" class="footnote" rel="footnote" role="doc-noteref">13</a></sup> regarding the West’s position in History. This was for our own good. How else could we see that the object, now AI, has no philology, much less philia? Far more than liberal democracy, the priority of objects and objectivity brings about the End of History.</p> <p>I am not sure that History necessarily progresses, but I am sure that words and ideas have been continually overloaded, because we continue to gather them up with all the things our languages can convey. This leads to a lot of dithering. It also leads to glut. Pruning is therefore always necessary – Ockham’s razor, yes, but really Stapledon’s cosmic division, or Borges’s garden shears, and lately in scientific fashion, “genetic scissors.” Because we all cherish the things we share through language, it saddens me just to write about them being cut away. But the roots will remain, <em>Inshallah</em>.</p> <p>Personally, I have decided that there are things which precede objects, and that there are objects which predate things. But it would be naïve and perhaps even unholy to believe that precedence in conception absolves a thing of its responsibility.</p> <p>Finally, I must go further East. <em>Mono no aware</em> (物の哀れ, ‘the pathos of things’ or ‘a sensitivity to ephemera’) is the most hauntingly beautiful idea I know. It means both object impermanence, and in our wistfulness at its passing, the transience of things. Sunsets and almond blossoms are beautiful things. We should all be so fortunate as to stay above the rubble and enjoy them. Blink and they disappear.</p> <hr/> <div class="footnotes" role="doc-endnotes"> <ol> <li id="fn:1"> <p>Mahmoud Darwish, <em>Like Almond Flowers or Further</em> (Riad El-Rayyes Books, 2005), p. 43. The translation is my own. <a href="#fnref:1" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:2"> <p>Bruno Latour, “Why has Critique Run Out of Steam? From Matters of Fact to Matters of Concern,” <em>Critical Inquiry</em> 30, no. 2 (2004): 225-248. <a href="#fnref:2" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:3"> <p>Alfred North Whitehead, <em>The Concept of Nature</em> (Cambridge University Press 1920). p. 29. <a href="#fnref:3" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:4"> <p>Latour, “Why has Critique Run Out of Steam?,” p. 246. <a href="#fnref:4" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:5"> <p>Martin Heidegger, “Das Ding,” in <em>Gesamtausgabe Band 7 – Vorträge und Aufsätze: Bauen</em>, edited by Friedrich-Wilhelm Von Hermann (Vittorio Klostermann, 2000). <a href="#fnref:5" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:6"> <p>Fouad Ben Ahmad and Rober Pasnau, “Ibn Rushd [Averroes],” <em>Stanford Encyclopedia of Philosophy</em> (2021), https://plato.stanford.edu/entries/ibn-rushd/. <a href="#fnref:6" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:7"> <p>II.1 {520}, in Ben Ahmad and Pasnau, “Ibn Rushd [Averroes].” <a href="#fnref:7" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:8"> <p>Shalom Sadik, “How Should We Read Maimonides’ <em>Guide of the Perplexed</em>? Clues From Al-Harizi’s Translation,” <em>Hebrew Union College Annual</em>, Vol. 93 (2022), p. 118. <a href="#fnref:8" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:9"> <p>Latour, “Why Has Critique Run Out of Steam?,” p. 235. <a href="#fnref:9" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:10"> <p>Lizzie Crook, “Everything changed in architecture after 9/11 attacks says Daniel Libeskind,” <em>Dezeen</em>, September 6, 2021, https://www.dezeen.com/2021/09/06/911-anniversary-daniel-libeskind-interview/. <a href="#fnref:10" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:11"> <p>Yuval Abraham, “’Lavender’: The AI machine directing Israel’s bombing spree in Gaza,” <em>+972 Magazine</em> / <em>Local Call</em> (שיחה מקומית), April 3, 2024, https://www.972mag.com/lavender-ai-israeli-army-gaza/. <a href="#fnref:11" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:12"> <p>Bill Brown, <em>Other Things</em> (University of Chicago Press, 2015), pp. 137. <a href="#fnref:12" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> <li id="fn:13"> <p>Suzanne Marchand, “German Orientalism and the Decline of the West,” <em>Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society</em> 145, no. 4 (2001), p. 465. <a href="#fnref:13" class="reversefootnote" role="doc-backlink">&#8617;</a></p> </li> </ol> </div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="essays"/><category term="gaza"/><category term="language"/><summary type="html"><![CDATA[A meditation on doubletalk written in a covid-induced fever dream.]]></summary></entry></feed>